<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel><title><![CDATA[Pompeii Consulting]]></title><description><![CDATA[IT Consulting | IT Management]]></description><link>http://localhost:2368/</link><generator>Ghost 0.8</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2016 23:57:38 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:2368/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[Offshoring at Global Information Systems, Inc.]]></title><description><![CDATA[Offshoring | Outsourcing | IT Consulting | IT Management | Information Technology Consulting | Information Technology Management | Pompeii Consulting]]></description><link>http://localhost:2368/information-technology-offshoring/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">9d484947-0dc9-4ef2-b990-6fe9fc01bbfe</guid><category><![CDATA[offshoring]]></category><category><![CDATA[onshoring]]></category><category><![CDATA[insourcing]]></category><category><![CDATA[Harvard Business Review]]></category><category><![CDATA[farshoring]]></category><category><![CDATA[nearshoring]]></category><category><![CDATA[backsourcing]]></category><category><![CDATA[captive center]]></category><category><![CDATA[outsourcing]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Pompeii Consulting]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2016 23:57:02 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>This case explores the topic of offshoring high-tech jobs several perspectives. The issues presented include determining the stock price consequences of offshoring, examining the economic consequences of the offshore job to both the transferring and receiving countries, considering the competitive consequences of not offshoring, and thinking through the challenge of investing in a career that is vulnerable to future offshoring.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://hbr.org/product/offshoring-at-global-information-systems-inc/204144-PDF-ENG" target="_blank">Harvard Business Review</a></p>

<p>Use the sourcing decision cycle framework in Chapter 9 and analyze the situation where Global Information Systems, Inc. was in 2004. What kind of outsourcing decision did it try to make?</p>

<p>In 2004, GIS had reached a point in the sourcing decision cycle framework where they needed to decide to keep the status quo or change its sourcing model.  GIS had previously established their own in-house programming centers in India, China, and Brazil.  These are examples of captive centers.  Going forward, however, GIS was looking not just to grow into these captive centers, but rather to actively move existing U.S. jobs offshore. </p>

<p>In deciding whether to “make or buy,” GIS weighed whether it should shift some of its IT capability from make to buy, specifically 3,000 programming jobs. These jobs, formerly domestically insourced positions, would be outsourced to existing GIS locations in China, India and Brazil. The reason for supporting this approach was that huge capacity expansion plus large price reductions made it more efficient to establish customer service/call centers, software development centers, engineering design centers, and back office accounting centers in low-cost areas of the world that were developing politically and socially reliable infrastructures.</p>

<p>Due to the political landscape with respect to outsourcing, GIS faced a tough decision to outsource domestically or internationally.  The company eventually chose an international outsourcing model which projected to save them $261 million per year in human capital expenditure. For example, “a U.S. programmer with a total employment cost (salary and all benefits) of $112,000 per year would be replaced by an offshore programmer with a total employment cost of $25,000 per year.” Although roughly 35% of those savings would be consumed by telecommunication and management costs, after an initial loss of $19 million the first year and a savings of only $40 million the second year, GIS would net $168 million per year in savings by outsourcing these positions, from the third year onward. </p>

<p>The decision GIS was trying to make, which was eventually supporting by Harding, was a shift from insourcing to offshoring.  More specifically, GIS was considering selective farshoring, since they were moving specific IT capabilities (programming) but not all job functions to distant lands, with the goal of substantial cost savings. </p>

<p><br></p>

<hr>

<p><br> <br>

What are the key assumptions that could make offshoring a "win-win" situation for both developed and developing economies? How should Jane Harding advise her son Jason?</p>

<p>Key assumptions that could make offshoring a “win-win” situation for both developed and developing economies are that the offshoring countries:</p>

<ul>
<li>Provide a cost savings through reduced labor costs </li>
<li>Provide highly educated and competent labor force</li>
<li>Provide continuing education to ensure support for technical upgrades</li>
<li>Ensure there are no language barriers</li>
<li>Ensure there is political stability</li>
<li>Have lower crime rates</li>
<li>Have friendly relations with the client company</li>
<li>Ensure security and/or trade restrictions</li>
<li>Keep company secrets and proprietary information private</li>
<li>Ensure availability of scalable technical infrastructure</li>
<li>Ensure cultural differences are known and negotiated prior to starting partnership</li>
<li>Account for time differences to ensure proper communication of deadlines</li>
</ul>

<p>Jane Harding’s son, Jason, requested advice on whether,  “he should pursue a degree in humanities or whether he should have a more ‘preprofessional’ focus to his studies such as on engineering, computer science or premed.”  When determining a career path, there are several areas to consider including career happiness (passion for the job), earning potential and stability of the chosen career path.</p>

<p>In considering the humanities,  there is no shortage of teachers in the workforce today and appears to be a sustainable long term career choice.  On the other hand, the mean annual salary is just under $80k, whereas premed for instance, has a mean salary in excess of $100k.</p>

<p>There are many factors that Jason must consider before making a decision, but it is also important that he becomes educated on the topic of outsourcing before deciding which area of study he will pursue. As technology evolves, locational dependencies become a much smaller factor when choosing a career path. Long-distance learning, and thus teaching, is becoming just as prevalent today as outsourced computer programming. The key for Jason’s success will be, not only the career path that he chooses, but the environment and and situation in which he does it. Although much of the traditional “Engineering” type work is being outsourced, there will always be parts of it that, for one reason or another, cannot be. For example, a network engineer that works for a public school may be replaceable through outsourcing, but the same job working for say a Department Of Defense school, for security reasons, may not be. When it comes down to the choice of which field of study is “safer,” there is not a definitive answer, because there are none. Jason must become educated in the field that he feels is right for him, and know that he will need to create a “niche” for himself in order to create his own job security. With technology breaking the restriction caused by location, this will likely be the case regardless of which field Jason decides to pursue.</p>

<p><a href="http://pompeiiconsulting.com/strategic-value-of-information-technology">Strategic Value of Information Technology</a></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Importance of Information]]></title><description><![CDATA[Game Theory | Prisoner's Dilema | IT Consulting | IT Management | Information Technology Consulting | Information Technology Management | Pompeii Consulting]]></description><link>http://localhost:2368/game-theory-imperfect-information/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6a8e6a40-57c4-47e4-a0d8-b1f6e005dac7</guid><category><![CDATA[game theory]]></category><category><![CDATA[invisible hand]]></category><category><![CDATA[imperfect information]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Pompeii Consulting]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2016 19:23:42 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="invisiblehand">Invisible Hand</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>By pursing his own interest, he frequently promotes that of the society more effectively than when he really intends to promote it... led by an invisible hand to promote an end which was no part of his intention</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Adam Smith</p>

<ul>
<li><p>conditions for perfectly competitive markets</p>

<ul><li>many buyers and sellers who are price takers</li>
<li>products are homogeneous</li>
<li>there are no barriers to entry or exit</li>
<li>perfect information about actions is available (not just complete information abut payoff and preference)</li></ul></li>
<li><p>perfectly competitive markets are only theoretically possible</p></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="effectsofimperfectinformation">Effects of Imperfect Information</h2>

<ul>
<li>game theory</li>
<li>prisoner's dilemma</li>
<li>choices
<ul><li>testify against the other</li>
<li>keep quiet</li></ul></li>
<li>neither knows what the other chooses</li>
<li>low prison time if neither confess</li>
<li>no prison time if you're the one to confess and the other does not</li>
<li>medium prison time if you both confess</li>
<li>Nash equilibrium where each person confesses is the worst situation</li>
<li>Pareto optimal where neither confesses is the best situation</li>
<li>John Nash won a Nobel prize in 1994</li>
<li>proved the existence of a t least one equilibrium point for any non-cooperative non zero-sum game with any numbers of players</li>
<li>market and invisible hand fails because only imperfect information and not complete information is available when players are choosing an action</li>
<li>information technology is especially useful in addressing this problem</li>
<li>information technology makes it easier to share information about actions among agents</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="http://pompeiiconsulting.com/strategic-value-of-information-technology">Strategic Value of Information Technology</a></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Information Technology Sourcing]]></title><description><![CDATA[Outsource| Insource | Offshore | IT Consulting | IT Management | Information Technology Consulting | Pompeii Consulting]]></description><link>http://localhost:2368/how-to-decide-when-to-outsource/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">64e15fac-91a1-43b0-b1a6-0d7847cf30ff</guid><category><![CDATA[outsourcing]]></category><category><![CDATA[insourcing]]></category><category><![CDATA[offshoring]]></category><category><![CDATA[onshoring]]></category><category><![CDATA[cloud]]></category><category><![CDATA[cloud computing]]></category><category><![CDATA[infrastructure as a service]]></category><category><![CDATA[IaaS]]></category><category><![CDATA[platform as a service]]></category><category><![CDATA[Paas]]></category><category><![CDATA[Software as a Service]]></category><category><![CDATA[Saas]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Pompeii Consulting]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2016 19:23:22 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1 id="informationtechnologysourcing">Information Technology Sourcing</h1>

<h2 id="sourcingdecisioncycleframework">Sourcing Decision Cycle Framework</h2>

<ul>
<li>sourcing involves many decisions</li>
<li>first step is the make or buy decision</li>
<li>if choose to buy must decide where</li>
<li>if the company decides to go offshore, must decide if offshore company is near or far</li>
<li>periodic evaluation must take place</li>
<li>continual evaluation is needed to determine if the arrangement is satisfactory or not, for both outsourcing and insourcing</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="itsourcingdecisiontree">IT Sourcing Decision Tree</h3>

<h4 id="makeorbuy">Make or Buy?</h4>

<ul>
<li>insourcing</li>
<li><p>outsourcing</p>

<ul><li>offshoring</li>
<li>onshoring</li>
<li>cloud</li></ul></li>
<li><p>offshoring</p>

<ul><li>captive center</li>
<li>farshoring</li>
<li>nearshoring</li></ul></li>
<li><p>evaluating status quo or change?</p>

<ul><li>backsourcing</li>
<li>stay</li></ul></li>
</ul>

<h3 id="makeorbuy">Make or Buy?</h3>

<p>Does it involve a core competency? <br>
If outsourced: Loss of control over strategic initiatives; loss of strategic focus</p>

<p>Does it involve confidential or sensitive IS services or software development? <br>
If outsourced: Competitive secrets may be leaked</p>

<p>Is there enough time available to complete software development projects in-house? <br>
If insourced: Project not completed on time</p>

<p>Do the in-house IS professionals have adequate training, experience, or skills to provide the service or develop the software? <br>
If outsourced: Technological innovations limited to what provider offers; overreliance on provider’s skills</p>

<p>Are there reliable outsourcing providers who are likely to stay in business for the duration of the contract? <br>
If outsourced: Project not completed, or, if completed, project is over budget and late when another provider takes it over</p>

<p>Is there an outsourcing provider that has a culture and practices that are compatible with the client? <br>
If outsourced: Conflict between client and provider personnel </p>

<p>Are there economies of scale that make it cheaper to provide the service or develop the software in-house? <br>
If outsourced: Costs of project or operations becomes excessive because of the way, the contract is written</p>

<p>Does it offer a better ability to handle peaks? <br>
If insourced: Loss of business </p>

<p>Does it involve consolidating data centers? <br>
If insourced: Inefficient operations</p>

<h3 id="insourcing">Insourcing</h3>

<ul>
<li>a firm provides information system services or develops information systems in its own in house information systems organization</li>
<li>this is the make decision</li>
<li>drivers that favor this decision:
<ul><li>keep core competencies in house</li>
<li>information system services or products that require considerable security or confidentiality</li>
<li>time available in house to complete information system projects</li>
<li>in house information technology personnel</li></ul></li>
<li>challenges to insourcing
<ul><li>getting needed information technology resources from management</li>
<li>competent information technology staff available</li></ul></li>
</ul>

<h3 id="outsourcing">Outsourcing</h3>

<ul>
<li>purchase of a good or service that was previously provided internally or that could be provided internally</li>
<li>driver that favor this decision:
<ul><li>cost reduction achieved through economies of scale (outsourcer may be able t negotiate lower prices on hardware and software)</li>
<li>help a company transition to new technologies through access to a larger information technology talent pool</li>
<li>brining in outside expertise can help management focus more on core activities rather than on information technology issues</li>
<li>outsourcing firms know how to hire, manage, and retain information technology staff</li>
<li>greater capacity on demand</li>
<li>overcome inertia to consolidate data centers</li>
<li>Offers costs savings</li>
<li>Eases transition to new technologies</li>
<li>Offers opportunity for better strategic focus</li>
<li>Provides better management of IS staff</li>
<li>Offers better ability to handle peaks</li>
<li>Easier to consolidate data centers</li>
<li>Provides a cash-infusion</li></ul></li>
<li>challenges to outsourcing
<ul><li>a degree of control is surrendered</li>
<li>lack of adequate anticipation of new techological capabilities when negotiating outsourcing contracts</li>
<li>company gives up any real potential to develop them for competitive advantage</li>
<li>contract terms may leave clients highly dependent on their providers</li>
<li>competitive secrets will be harder to keep</li>
<li>savings may never be realized</li>
<li>dealing with multiple outsourcing vendors</li>
<li>Maintains an adequate level of control</li>
<li>Maintains ability to respond to technological innovation</li>
<li>Avoids loss of strategic advantage</li>
<li>Avoids overreliance on outsourcing provider</li>
<li>Mitigates outsourcing risks</li>
<li>Ensures cost savings while protecting quality</li>
<li>Works effectively with suppliers</li></ul></li>
</ul>

<h4 id="avoidingoutsourcingrisks">Avoiding Outsourcing Risks</h4>

<ul>
<li>do not negotiate solely on price</li>
<li>craft full life cycle service contracts that occur in stages</li>
<li>establish short term contracts</li>
<li>use multiple best of breed suppliers</li>
<li>hone skills in contract management</li>
<li>carefully evaluate your company's own capabilities</li>
<li>choose an outsourcing provider whose capabilities complement yours</li>
<li>base a choice on cultural fit as well as technical expertise</li>
<li>determine whether a particular outsourcing relationship produces a net benefit for your company</li>
<li>plan transition to outsourcing</li>
<li>use SOAs to increase agility</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="fullversusselectiveoutsourcing">Full versus Selective Outsourcing</h4>

<ul>
<li>full outsourcing implies that an enterprise outsources all of its information system function from desktop services to software development</li>
<li>selective outsourcing or strategic outsourcing means an enterprise chooses which information technology capabilities to retain in house and which to give to an outsider</li>
<li>in a best of breed approach suppliers are chosen for their expertise in a specific technology area such as:
<ul><li>web site hosting</li>
<li>web 2.0</li>
<li>applications</li>
<li>business process application development</li>
<li>help desk support</li>
<li>networking and communications</li>
<li>social information technology services</li>
<li>data center operations</li></ul></li>
</ul>

<h4 id="onshoring">Onshoring</h4>

<ul>
<li>onshoring or inshoring is the performing outsourcing work domestically</li>
<li>onshoring may be considered the opposite of offshoring</li>
<li>rural sourcing, hiring outside providers with operations in rural parts of America, is a growing trend</li>
<li>lower salaries</li>
<li>lower living costs</li>
<li>closer time zones</li>
<li>similar culture</li>
<li>fewer hassles than dealing with foreign outsourcing providers</li>
<li>too small to handle large scale projects</li>
<li>may not have the most technologically advanced employees</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="offshoring">Offshoring</h4>

<ul>
<li>the most general term for outsourcing abroad</li>
<li>sometimes short for offshore outsourcing</li>
<li>the information technology organization uses contractor services or even builds its own data center in a distant land</li>
<li>substantial potential cost savings through reduced labor costs</li>
<li>some countries offer a very well educated labor force</li>
<li>implementation of quantity standards
<ul><li>six sigma</li>
<li>ISO 9001</li></ul></li>
<li>offshoring can either be in a distant land
<ul><li>farshoring</li></ul></li>
<li>offshoring can be in relatively close proximity
<ul><li>nearshoring</li></ul></li>
<li>Farshoring is a form of offshoring that involves sourcing service work to a foreign, lower wage country that is far away in distance or time zone or both like India or China</li>
<li>Nearshoring is when work is sourced to a foreign, lower wage country that is relatively close in distance or time zone like Costa Rica</li>
<li>captive center is an overseas subsidiary that is set up to serve the parent company and operates like an outsourcing provider but is owned by the firm</li>
<li>captive center can be farshore or nearshore</li>
</ul>

<h5 id="offshoringdestinationselection">Offshoring Destination Selection</h5>

<ul>
<li>what makes countries attractive for offshoring?</li>
<li>high English language proficiency</li>
<li>countries that are politically stable</li>
<li>countries with lower crime rates</li>
<li>countries with friendly relationships</li>
<li>security and/or trade restrictions</li>
<li>level of technical infrastructure available</li>
<li>India makes an entire industry based of offshoring</li>
<li>SEI's capability maturity model (CMM)
<ul><li>levels 1-5</li>
<li>India has CMM level 5 software development processes</li>
<li>extremely reliable and desirable as vendors</li></ul></li>
<li>level of development of a country will determine if the location is appropriate</li>
<li>three tiers of software exporting nations</li>
<li>Tier 1
<ul><li>mature software exporting nations</li>
<li>highly industrialized nations</li>
<li>US</li>
<li>UK</li>
<li>Japan</li>
<li>India</li></ul></li>
<li>Tier 2
<ul><li>emerging software exporting nations</li>
<li>up and comers</li>
<li>small populations</li>
<li>political instability</li>
<li>Brazil</li></ul></li>
<li>Tier 3
<ul><li>infant stage software exporting nations</li>
<li>not significantly impacting on the software industry</li>
<li>Cuba</li>
<li>Jordan</li></ul></li>
<li>cultural differences have to be carefully addressed</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="cloudcomputing">Cloud Computing</h3>

<ul>
<li>a third party provided information technology services over the internet</li>
<li>provides an entire data center's worth of servers, networking services, system management, security, storage, and other infrastructure</li>
<li>clients buy the exact amount of storage, computing power, security, or other information technology functions they need when they need it and pay only for what they use
<ul><li>possible cost savings</li></ul></li>
<li>24/7 access from multiple mobile devices</li>
<li>high availability for large backup data storage</li>
<li>ease of use</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="infrastructureasaservice">Infrastructure as a Service</h4>

<ul>
<li>IaaS</li>
<li>provides infrastructure through grids or clusters or virtualized servers, networks, storage, and systems software</li>
<li>designed to augment or replace the functions of an entire data center</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="platformasaservice">Platform as a Service</h4>

<ul>
<li>PaaS</li>
<li>provides services using virtualized servers on which clients can run existing applications or develop new ones without having to worry about maintaining the operating systems, server hardware, load balancing, or computing capacity</li>
<li>provider manages the hardware and underlying operating system</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="softwareasaservice">Software as a Service</h4>

<ul>
<li>SaaS</li>
<li>Application as a Service
<ul><li>ASP
software application functionality through a web browser  </li></ul></li>
<li>the platform and infrastructure are fully managed by the cloud provider</li>
<li>if the operating system or underlying service isn’t configured correctly the data at the higher application layer may be at risk</li>
<li>the most widely know and used form of cloud computing</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="reevaluation">Reevaluation</h3>

<ul>
<li>status quo or change?</li>
<li>backsourcing means a company takes back in house assets activates and skills that were previously outsourced to one or more outside information system providers</li>
<li>companies backsource after terminating, renegotiating, or letting their contracts expire</li>
<li>the reasons given for backsourcing often mirror the reasons for outsourcing</li>
<li>outsourcing decisions can be difficult and expensive to revers requiring the company to acquire the necessary information technology infrastructure and staff</li>
<li>backsourcing is followed by another cycle of decisions as the company responds to its dynamic environment</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="http://pompeiiconsulting.com/strategic-value-of-information-technology">Strategic Value of Information Technology</a></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Air Canada Case Study]]></title><description><![CDATA[Operational Excellence | Customer Proximity | IT Consulting | IT Management | Information Technology Consulting | Pompeii Consulting]]></description><link>http://localhost:2368/air-canada-information-technology-management/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">eeb72fca-3d17-4278-9eb4-e5e0539b6d45</guid><category><![CDATA[information technology]]></category><category><![CDATA[information management]]></category><category><![CDATA[CIO]]></category><category><![CDATA[case study]]></category><category><![CDATA[competitive advantage]]></category><category><![CDATA[outsourcing]]></category><category><![CDATA[airlines]]></category><category><![CDATA[IT strategy]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Pompeii Consulting]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2016 00:42:55 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>By covering information technology (IT) management at Air Canada over two decades, this case illustrates the process of alignment between IT and business over time. During the 1990s, the focus was on efficiency and the IT department supported business through both the centralization of the IT function and the outsourcing of most of the IT activities, with the explicit objective of reducing costs. Twenty years later, at the time the case takes place, Air Canada had two key strategic objectives: operational excellence and customer proximity. In order to help meet these two objectives, IT now supported business through a hybrid structure and an innovation-based, "best-of-breed" sourcing strategy. Also, over the years, the IT department at Air Canada had developed processes aimed at ensuring efficient delivery of services by suppliers, as well as in-house processes to scan, identify and implement innovative IT solutions both for operational excellence and customer proximity.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://cb.hbsp.harvard.edu/cbmp/product/HEC045-PDF-ENG" target="_blank">Harvard Business Publishing</a></p>

<p>Managing the information resource of a firm focused on both “engaging with customers” and competing “more effectively on multiple levels against the low-pricing structures offered by low-cost carriers” entailed many challenges, which Air Canada’s CIO and her team had been addressing in multiple ways. How was Air Canada addressing these challenges in 2011? </p>

<p>In 2010, Air Canada was already a thriving empire in the airline industry. They had gone through an extreme period of growth and partnered with many world renowned airlines and formed the Star Alliance. As 2011 approached,  Air Canada’s business strategy shifted from expansion to sustainment. In response to this strategy shift, two main business goals were developed: cost reduction and improved customer engagement. In order to reach their new business goals, they focused on three main areas that included “operational process improvements, supplier contract renegotiations and revenue productivity gains.”  </p>

<p>In 2011, efforts were focused on improving efficiency in these three areas;  therefore, they  implemented a “multi-vendor strategy in order to benefit from specialized, best-of-breed airline products available in the market more quickly and less expensively.”  A better sourcing strategy was needed which led to IBM being assigned to act as the “integrator” and  as the “keeper and guardian of Air Canada’s corporate standards.”  During this time, Air Canada also  moved to a relational approach “to manage its outsourcing contracts with multiple vendors.” To the CIO, “having a successful IT outsourcing contract meant being accountable for the problems that arise and taking a collaborative approach with vendors to problem solve.”</p>

<p>Aligned closely to a matrix organizational structure, the IT department had been reorganized to a new structure  and “an IT representative was assigned to each of the three main branches:  Customers, Commercials and Operation.” This new structure ensured that there was “one common goal: to link the business side and IT,” and that “new solutions had to add value to the business, be in line with corporate standards, and potentially contribute to the overall cost savings.”  Through this new reorganization and  implementation of IT, not only was cost reduction achieved, but customer engagement was also improved. By linking all IT within the organization, information was able to be shared throughout every department and improved the customer experience. Additionally, the Electronic Customer Relationship Management (e-CRM) team was developed, and through the sharing of  information this team was able to gather intimate knowledge on its’ customers and provide for their individual requirements.</p>

<p><br></p>

<hr>

<p><br></p>

<p>In aligning its business and IT strategies, how did Air Canada cope with <a href="http://pompeiiconsulting.com/strategic-alignment" target="_blank">the five competitive forces</a>? In order to further improve its business-IT alignment, what areas should Air Canada target next and what actions should it take?</p>

<p>Air Canada recognized that in order to compete with low-cost carriers, it would require reducing costs.  Air Canada’s number one cost was fuel, which they had no control over; therefore, they instituted a Cost Transformation Program (CTP) focusing on “operational process improvements, supplier contract renegotiations, and revenue productivity gains.”  Air Canada’s strategy for coping with the five competitive forces included: <br>
Potential threat of new entrants -  Improved operational processes by entering major partnerships with Lufthansa and United/Continental.  These partnerships created barriers to entry for new airlines, who would struggle to compete with Air Canada’s global reach. Air Canada accomplished this through large investments in IT,  which allowed them to  maintain high quality and competitive  services with low cost carriers.   </p>

<p>Bargaining power of buyers - Allowed competition with the low-cost carriers as part of the CTP..  Lowered costs were achieved by using IT to optimize processes like the ones used by the pilots and crews for choosing flights.  The addition of customer facing systems, such as allowing customers to upgrade online or on mobile devices, increased buyer’s bargaining power in a mutually beneficial way. </p>

<p>Bargaining power of suppliers - In 2011, used multiple vendors to accomplish a bulk of its IT needs, thus lowering the leverage to each supplier.  Air Canada assigned IBM to be the integrator of each vendor’s product, ensuring a seamless fit with current and legacy systems. Additionally, contract negotiations were accomplished through the use of Requests for Proposals which breeds competition. </p>

<p>Threat of substitute products - Made the “cost” of switching airlines higher by being the first to introduce electronic boarding passes and then iPhone and BlackBerry applications.  The convenience Air Canada provided the customer likely factored into the decision-making process of the customers potentially considering switching airlines. </p>

<p>Industry competitors - Acquired their main rival (Canadian Airlines) and created partnerships with major airlines (Lufthansa/United Continental).  Using IT to drive costs down through innovation kept Air Canada a step ahead of its competitors.</p>

<p>Next areas for Air Canada to target should include the performance of research into the IT-business strategy of the major airlines with whom they partner.  Joint IT-business meetings between the partners could result in lessons learned for both sides, potentially lead to better integration of functionality between airlines and improve data sharing.  Investment in data analytics and analysis of customer, operational, and/or shared data for business intelligence should also be explored. .  </p>

<p>Future Air Canada actions should include having  the CIO and business teams from Air Canada, Lufthansa, and United/Continental meet on a regular basis.  The purpose of these meetings should include discussing and planning ways to integrate IT capability which ultimately will result in an increase in value to the customers and to the businesses.  </p>

<p><a href="http://pompeiiconsulting.com/strategic-value-of-information-technology">Strategic Value of Information Technology</a></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Information Technology Valuation]]></title><description><![CDATA[Real Options | IT Investment | IT Portfolio | CIO | IT Consulting | IT Management | Pompeii Consulting]]></description><link>http://localhost:2368/information-technology-portfolio-management-investing/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">d4b7fc98-eff6-45e3-8d91-448aa39406b2</guid><category><![CDATA[financial instruments]]></category><category><![CDATA[capital budgeting]]></category><category><![CDATA[corporate finance]]></category><category><![CDATA[chief information officer]]></category><category><![CDATA[CIO]]></category><category><![CDATA[real options]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Pompeii Consulting]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 19:22:12 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="businessinformationtechnologymaturitymodel">Business Information Technology Maturity Model</h2>

<h3 id="level1businessefficiency">Level 1 Business Efficiency</h3>

<h4 id="level1businessdemand">Level 1 Business Demand</h4>

<ul>
<li>foundation systems</li>
<li>cost savings</li>
<li>operation information</li>
<li>functional orientation</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="level1itfocus">Level 1 IT Focus</h4>

<ul>
<li>provide basic services and systems</li>
<li>stabilize operation and support</li>
<li>improve business processes</li>
<li>IT management fundamentals</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="level2businesseffectiveness">Level 2 Business Effectiveness</h3>

<h4 id="level2businessdemand">Level 2 Business Demand</h4>

<ul>
<li>business network and process redesign</li>
<li>enable business and partnerships</li>
<li>enterprise process solutions</li>
<li>management information</li>
<li>process orientation</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="level2itfocus">Level 2 IT Focus</h4>

<ul>
<li>establish common IT infrastructure</li>
<li>meet customer’s expectations</li>
<li>build IT credibility </li>
<li>improve solution delivery</li>
<li>establish enterprise architecture</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="level3businesstransformation">Level 3 Business Transformation</h3>

<h4 id="level3businessdemand">Level 3 Business Demand</h4>

<ul>
<li>inter enterprise systems and infrastructure</li>
<li>business growth</li>
<li>innovation</li>
<li>rapid reconfiguration capability</li>
<li>market information</li>
<li>business integration orientation</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="level3itfocus">Level 3 IT Focus</h4>

<ul>
<li>continuous planning</li>
<li>converge business and IT</li>
<li>expand and extend infrastructure</li>
<li>enable flexibility and agility</li>
<li>innovation and value</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="itorganizationactivities">IT Organization Activities</h2>

<ul>
<li>Developing and Maintaining Systems
<ul><li>Work together with business users to analyze needs, design the software, write or code the software, and test it to make sure it works and meets the business objectives; identify, acquire, and install outside software packages to fill business needs; maintain systems; address post-implementation needs, such as correcting system errors or enhancing the system to respond to changing business environments and governmental regulations.</li>
<li>Level 1</li></ul></li>
<li>Managing Supplier Relationships
<ul><li>Maximize the benefit of supplier relationships to the enterprise and preempt problems that might occur. </li>
<li>Level 1</li></ul></li>
<li>Managing Data, Information, and Knowledge
<ul><li>Database administration: collect and store data created, developed, or discovered by the enterprise (Level 1); manage enterprise information and knowledge (Level 2).</li>
<li>Level 1,2</li></ul></li>
<li>Managing Internet and Network Systems
<ul><li>Develop and maintain Internet capabilities; manage private networks, telephone systems, access to the Internet, and new wireless technologies; design network architecture; build and maintain the network infrastructure.</li>
<li>Level 1,2 (depending on nature of network)</li></ul></li>
<li>Managing Human Resources
<ul><li>Provide sufficient business and technical training so that staff can perform effectively and retain their value to the enterprise; hire staff; work to retain staff; fire poor performers; track time; work with enterprise HR personnel, who may be familiar with interviewing approaches, personnel laws, regulations, and trends.</li>
<li>Level 1</li></ul></li>
<li>Operating the Data Center
<ul><li>Operate and maintain large mainframe computers, rows of servers, or other platforms on which the company’s data and business applications reside, or other hardware.</li>
<li>Level 1</li></ul></li>
<li>Providing General Support
<ul><li>Varies but may include helpdesk activities: maintain the first client contact through a centralized helpdesk even for such diverse services as networking and telecommunications; collect pertinent information, record it, determine its priority, contact the appropriate support personnel, and follow up with the business contacts with updates or resolution information.</li>
<li>Level 1</li></ul></li>
<li>Planning for Business Discontinuities
<ul><li>Develop and implement business continuity plan to counter terrorist attacks, intentional fraud, hurricanes, tornadoes, floods, or other man-made and natural disasters that could cripple the enterprise.</li>
<li>Level 1</li></ul></li>
<li>Innovating Current Processes
<ul><li>Work with managers to innovate processes that can benefit from technological solutions (i.e., Social IT, installing voice mail to networking personal computers, automating general ledger transactions, ERP implementations); design systems that facilitate new ways of doing business.</li>
<li>Level 2</li></ul></li>
<li>Establishing Architecture Platforms and Standards
<ul><li>Develop, maintain, and communicate standards; ensure consistent data so that the integrity of a data warehouse won’t be undermined.</li>
<li>Level 2</li></ul></li>
<li>Promoting Enterprise Security
<ul><li>Maintain the integrity of the enterprise infrastructure; implement enterprise information security strategy; identify and prioritize threats to the enterprise’s information assets; develop and implement security policies and technical controls and infrastructure to address each threat; work with the business units to make their operational practices more secure and to train employees about security risks and the importance of security to their work; implement an awareness program that keeps security on employees’ minds as they deal with information on a daily basis; participate in discussions about security investments.</li>
<li>Level 2</li></ul></li>
<li>Anticipating New Technologies
<ul><li>Scout new technology trends and help the business integrate them into planning and operations; assess the costs and benefits of new technologies for the enterprise; work closely with business groups to determine which technologies can provide the greatest benefit, how the technologies might affect the organization, how they might advance the business strategy, and when they should be implemented; ensure that the enterprise does not invest heavily in new technologies that quickly become obsolete or incompatible with other enterprise standards.</li>
<li>Level 3</li></ul></li>
<li>Participating in Setting and Implementing Strategic Goals
<ul><li>Enable business managers to achieve strategic goals by acting as consultants or by teaching them about developing technologies; advise managers on best practices within IT and work with them to develop IT enhanced solutions to business problems; educate managers about current technologies; serve as partners in moving the enterprise forward.</li>
<li>Level 3</li></ul></li>
<li>Integrating the Use of Social IT
<ul><li>Leverage the use of social IT to create a business transformation; transform social IT from personal to business use; provide customer-, supplier-, and employee-facing applications for engagement, collaboration, and innovation; and manage the data resulting from social IT to provide business insights.</li>
<li>Level 3</li></ul></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="buildingabusinesscaseforit">Building a Business Case for IT</h2>

<p>IT organization is charged with providing solutions</p>

<p>An IT business case</p>

<ul>
<li>created to gain support and go ahead decision on an IT proposal</li>
<li>is similar to a legal case</li>
<li>is a structured document that lays out all of the relevant information needed to make a go no-go decision</li>
<li>helps establish priorities for investing in different projects</li>
<li>identifies how IT and the business can deliver new benefits</li>
<li>gains commitment from business managers</li>
<li>creates a basis for monitoring the investment</li>
</ul>

<p>A framework for identifying and describing both financial and non-financial benefits for a cost-risk-benefit analysis for a business case </p>

<h2 id="itportfoliomanagement">IT Portfolio Management</h2>

<ul>
<li>IT portfolio management refers to the process of evaluating and approving IT investments as they relate to other current and potential IT investments</li>
<li>IT investments should be managed as any other investments would be managed by an organization</li>
<li>involves picking the right mix of investments to enjoy synergy, in lower risks and greater returns</li>
<li>don’t put all of your eggs in one basket</li>
<li>goal is to invest in most valuable IT initiatives that generate maximum benefits</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="assetclassesofitportfolio">Asset Classes of IT Portfolio</h2>

<p>Four assets classes of IT investments</p>

<h3 id="infrastructuresystems">Infrastructure Systems</h3>

<ul>
<li>the base foundation of shared information technology services used for multiple applications</li>
<li>46% of IT expenditure</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="transactionalsystems">Transactional Systems</h3>

<ul>
<li>systems that streamline or cut costs on business operations</li>
<li>25% of IT expenditure</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="informationsystems">Information Systems</h3>

<ul>
<li>systems that provide information to control, manage, communicate, analyze, or collaborate</li>
<li>18% of IT expenditure</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="strategicsystem">Strategic System</h3>

<ul>
<li>system used to gain competitive advantage in the market place</li>
<li>11% of IT expenditure</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="valuingitinvestments">Valuing IT Investments</h2>

<p>IT investments are difficult to assess value for because:</p>

<ul>
<li>IT can be a significant part of the annual budget, thus under close scrutiny</li>
<li>the systems themselves are complex and calculating the costs is an art not a science</li>
<li>many IT investments are for infrastructure; the payback period is much longer than other capital investments</li>
<li>oftentimes the payback cannot be calculated because the investment is a necessity rather than a choice</li>
<li>there is no tangible payback</li>
</ul>

<p>IT investment valuation is necessary</p>

<h3 id="approachestoitvaluation">Approaches to IT Valuation</h3>

<ul>
<li>Return on Investment (ROI)
<ul><li>ROI= (Estimated lifetime benefits - Estimated lifetime costs) / (Estimated lifetime costs)</li></ul></li>
<li>Net Present Value (NPV)
<ul><li>Calculated by discounting the costs and benefits for each year of system’s lifetime using present value (PV)</li>
<li>Discounted Cash Flow (DCF)</li></ul></li>
<li>Economic Value Added (EVA)
<ul><li>EVA = (net operating profit after taxes) – (capital) x (weighted average cost of capital)</li></ul></li>
<li>Payback Analysis
<ul><li>Time that will lapse before accrued benefits overtake accrued and continuing costs</li></ul></li>
<li>Internal Rate of Return (IRR)
<ul><li>Return that the IT investment is compared to the corporate policy on rate of return</li></ul></li>
<li>Weighted Scoring Methods
<ul><li>Costs and revenues/savings are weighted based on their strategic importance, etc.</li></ul></li>
<li>Prototyping
<ul><li>A scaled-down version of a system is tested for its costs and benefits</li></ul></li>
<li>Game Theory or Role-playing
<ul><li>These approaches may surface behavioral changes or new tasks attributable to a new system</li></ul></li>
<li>Simulation
<ul><li>A model is used to test the impact of a new system or series of tasks; low-cost method</li></ul></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="optionspricing">Options Pricing</h2>

<ul>
<li>NPV involves only tow choices
<ul><li>we do</li>
<li>we don't</li></ul></li>
<li>options pricing allows one to take future action in response to uncertainty about changes in the business environment</li>
<li>offers a risk hedge strategy to minimize negative impact of risk by waiting to see what happens</li>
<li>applicable when
<ul><li>an investment can be deferred</li>
<li>a balance between waiting for information and forgoing revenues</li>
<li>emerging investments</li>
<li>prototyping investment</li>
<li>technology as product investments</li></ul></li>
<li>Used along with DCF when the decision to pursue an investment can be deferred for some period of time</li>
<li>many investments particularly strategic ones like IT bear a strong resemblance to a financial call option</li>
<li>a call option is an option but not an obligation to buy an asset with value (S) by paying a pre-set price (X) on or before a certain point in time
<ul><li>European Option: on a specific date</li>
<li>American Option: on or before a specific date</li></ul></li>
<li>NPV only allows managers to make a decision now on an asset and then see what happens</li>
<li>managers can get to wait and see what happens, until some uncertainty is resolved and then make decision to invest or not</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="realoptions">Real Options</h3>

<ul>
<li>real options allow managers to defer investment decisions and enjoy:
<ul><li>reduced uncertainty</li>
<li>interest income earned on deferred expenditure</li></ul></li>
<li>Requires
<ul><li>set up a mapping between a project and a call option</li>
<li>related the option to a DCF valuation and perform an option valuation</li>
<li>extract managerial insights from the option pricing framework</li>
<li>call option valuation model is the Black-Scholes Model</li>
<li>option analysis complements but does not replace DCF NPV</li></ul></li>
</ul>

<h3 id="mappingitprojecttorealoption">Mapping IT Project to Real Option</h3>

<ul>
<li>S Stock price
<ul><li>PV of IT project's assets to be acquired</li>
<li>PV (assets to be acquired)</li></ul></li>
<li>X Exercise price
<ul><li>IT expenditure needed to acquire the assets</li>
<li>PV (expenditure)</li></ul></li>
<li>Time to expiration
<ul><li>decision deferral period</li>
<li>t</li></ul></li>
<li>Risk free interest rate
<ul><li>time value of money</li>
<li>r</li></ul></li>
<li>Variance of return or stock
<ul><li>risk of IT project's assets</li>
<li>σ2</li></ul></li>
</ul>

<h3 id="relatingdcftooptionvaluation">Relating DCF to Option Valuation</h3>

<ul>
<li>NPV = PV(asset) - PV(expenditure now) = S - X</li>
<li>Invest now if NPV > 0 </li>
<li>NPVq = PV(asset) / PV(expenditure later)</li>
<li>Project is in the money if NPVq >1</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="optionvaluation">Option Valuation</h3>

<ul>
<li>Project risk is the variability of return on the project per unit of time measured by the variance of return σ2</li>
<li>multiplying the variance per unit of time by the time periods remaining gives cumulative variance σ2t</li>
<li>cumulative volatility = σ√t</li>
<li>knowing NPVq and σ√t we can lookup the Black-Scholes determinant, a percentage %, from a table</li>
</ul>

<p>￼###Information Technology Project Real Options</p>

<h4 id="optioni">Option I</h4>

<ul>
<li>NPV > 0 </li>
<li>t = 0</li>
<li>invest Now</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="optionii">Option II</h4>

<ul>
<li>NPV > 0 </li>
<li>NPVq > 1</li>
<li>t ~= 0 </li>
<li>exercise option early or maybe now</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="optioniii">Option III</h4>

<ul>
<li>NPV &lt; 0</li>
<li>NPVq > 1 </li>
<li>t > 0</li>
<li>probably invest later</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="optioniv">Option IV</h4>

<ul>
<li>NPV &lt; 0 </li>
<li>NPVq &lt; 1</li>
<li>t > 0</li>
<li>maybe invest later</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="optionv">Option V</h4>

<ul>
<li>NPV &lt; 0</li>
<li>NPVq &lt; 1</li>
<li>t ~= 0</li>
<li>probably never invest</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="optionvi">Option VI</h4>

<ul>
<li>NPV &lt; 0</li>
<li>t = 0</li>
<li>invest never</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="managerialinsightofrealoptions">Managerial Insight of Real Options</h3>

<ul>
<li>natural tug: options tend to move up in the real option as time passes</li>
<li>only tow forces can push a real option up before time runs out: good luck and active management</li>
<li>managers can increase value and reduce cost to move the option to the real option up</li>
<li>be careful of spillover effects in an option portfolio and nested options in an IT strategy (an option that influences other options in a series of decisions)</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="potentialissuesofitrealoptions">Potential Issues of IT Real Options</h3>

<ul>
<li>uncertainties and risks in real options add a new element to the capital budgeting problem</li>
<li>σ is usually between 20% and 40%</li>
<li>many investment decisions are complex with interdependencies and synergies among projects and options</li>
<li>IT investments often do not result in easily measured cash flows</li>
<li>little account is taken of less tangible outcomes such as business processes, marketing, customer services, and a firm's competitiveness</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="itinvestmentmonitoring">IT Investment Monitoring</h2>

<ul>
<li>if you can’t measure it, you can’t manage it</li>
<li>management needs to make sure that the money spent on IT leads to organizational benefit</li>
<li>metrics for monitoring IT investments
<ul><li>financial: ROI, NPV</li>
<li>system: log of errors, downtime, response time</li>
<li>business: revenues generated from web sales</li></ul></li>
<li>comprehensive monitoring approaches
<ul><li>balanced score card</li>
<li>dashboard</li></ul></li>
</ul>

<h3 id="balancedscorecard">Balanced Scorecard</h3>

<ul>
<li>focus attention on the organization's value drivers </li>
<li>focus on financial performance</li>
<li>look at business from four perspectives
<ul><li>customer</li>
<li>internal</li>
<li>business</li>
<li>innovation and learning</li>
<li>financial</li></ul></li>
<li>questions to ask
<ul><li>how do customers and users see us?</li>
<li>at what must we excel?</li>
<li>can we continue to improve and create value?</li>
<li>how do we look to shareholders?</li></ul></li>
<li>apply balanced scorecard to IT means interpreting categories more broadly</li>
<li>IT scorecard is linked to corporate scorecard by insuring IT measures used support the corporate goals</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="balancedscorecardappliedtoinformationtechnology">Balanced Scorecard Applied to Information Technology</h4>

<ul>
<li>Customer
<ul><li>Measures that reflect factors that really matter to customers</li>
<li>User defined operational metrics</li></ul></li>
<li>Internal Business
<ul><li>Measures of what the company must do internally to meet customer expectations.</li>
<li>IT process metrics, project completion rates, system operational performance metrics</li></ul></li>
<li>Innovating and Learning
<ul><li>Measures of the company’s ability to innovate, improve and learn</li>
<li>IT R&amp;D, New technology introduction success rate, training metrics</li></ul></li>
<li><p>Financial</p>

<ul><li>Measures to indicate contribution of activities to the bottom-line</li>
<li>IT project ROI, NPV, IRR, cost/benefit, TCO, ABC</li></ul>

<h3 id="informationtechnologydashboards">Information Technology Dashboards</h3>

<ul><li>IT dashboards summarize key metrics for managers in a way that provides quick identification of the status of the organization's IT activities</li>
<li>IT dashboards provide frequently updated information on areas of interest about IT operations</li>
<li>data tends to focus on project status or operational system status</li>
<li>problems can also be identified and handled more promptly</li>
<li>built on information contained in other apps, databases, and analytical systems</li>
<li>business intelligence</li></ul>

<h4 id="architectureofanitdashboard">Architecture of an IT Dashboard</h4>

<ul><li>Raw Data</li>
<li>feeds transaction system</li>
<li>drive cost</li>
<li>customer order</li>
<li>customer payment</li>
<li>test data</li>
<li>build data</li>
<li>Fictional Applications</li>
<li>transaction based</li>
<li>standard reporting</li>
<li>highly focused</li>
<li>ERP</li>
<li>logistics</li>
<li>point of sale (POS)</li>
<li>supplier quality system</li>
<li>manufacturing execution system</li>
<li>marginal monitoring system</li>
<li>failure analysis system</li>
<li>Business Intelligence</li>
<li>cross application query</li>
<li>data mining</li>
<li>statistical analysis</li>
<li>BMIS</li>
<li>financial performance</li>
<li>mitec reporting</li>
<li>factory reporting</li>
<li>QIS</li>
<li>product performance</li>
<li>Dashboards</li>
<li>highly summarized</li>
<li>key metric driven</li>
<li>visualization</li>
<li>alerts</li>
<li>Corporate Dashboards</li>
<li>planning</li>
<li>forecasting</li>
<li>revenue positions</li>
<li>inventory positions</li>
<li>Factory Dashboard</li>
<li>component inventory</li>
<li>line utilization</li>
<li>yield</li></ul>

<h2 id="fundingitresources">Funding IT Resources</h2>

<p>Who pays?</p>

<ul><li>users</li>
<li>IT department </li>
<li>corporate</li></ul>

<p>Funding Methods</p>

<ul><li>chargeback</li>
<li>allocation</li>
<li>corporate budget</li></ul>

<h3 id="chargeback">Chargeback</h3>

<ul><li>IT costs are recovered by charging individuals, departments, or business units based on actual usage</li>
<li>rates of usage are calculated based on the actual cost to the IT group to run the system and billed out on a regular basis </li>
<li>charge is popular because it is viewed as the most equitable way to recover IT costs</li>
<li>creating and managing chargeback system is a costly endeavor due to the need to collect extensive system usage data</li>
<li>done for management reasons</li></ul>

<h3 id="allocation">Allocation</h3>

<ul><li>recovers costs based on some simplified metrics other than usage such as revenues, log-in accounts, or number of employees</li>
<li>its primary advantage is that it is simpler to implement and apply</li>
<li>free rider problem</li>
<li>deciding the basis for charging out the costs can be a problem</li>
<li>true up process is needed where total IT expenses are compared to total IT funds recovered from the business units</li>
<li>done for management reasons</li></ul>

<h3 id="corporatebudget">Corporate Budget</h3>

<ul><li>here the costs fall to the corporate bottom line rather than levying charges on specific users or business units</li>
<li>no requirement to calculate prices of the IT systems and hence no financial concerns raised monthly by business managers</li>
<li><p>IT has to compete with all other budgeted items for funds</p></li>
<li><p>chargeback, allocation, corporate budget treat IT as a cost center not a profit center</p></li>
<li>most bac=sic method of determining costs is to add up all of the hardware, software, network, and people involved in Information Systems.</li>
<li>real cost is not as easy to determine</li>
<li>most companies continue to use this over-simplistic view of determining cost and never really know the real cost</li></ul>

<h3 id="activitybasedcosting">Activity Based Costing</h3>

<ul><li>activity based costing (ABC) counts the actual activities that go into making a specific product or delivering a specific service</li>
<li>activities are processes, function, or tasks that occur over time and have recognized results</li>
<li>activities consume assigned resources to produce products and services</li>
<li>activates are useful in costing because they are the common denominator between business process improvement and information improvement</li>
<li>ABC charges all costs to profit centers not cost centers</li></ul>

<h2 id="totalcostofownership">Total Cost of Ownership</h2>

<ul><li>Total cost of ownership (TCO) is becoming the industry standard</li>
<li>TCO looks beyond initial capital investments to include support, administration, and training costs,</li>
<li>TCO estimates annual costs per user for each infrastructure choice, costs are then totaled</li>
<li>TCO estimates should be computed per component to provide the best investment numbers to compare with financial return number IT real options</li>
<li>TCO helps managers understand how infrastructure cost break down</li>
<li>it provides a more complete picture of where managers spend their IT dollars as TCO results can be evaluated over time against industry standards</li></ul></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="chiefinformationofficercio">Chief Information Officer (CIO)</h2>

<ul>
<li>Chief technology officer (CTO) Track emerging technologies; advise on technology adoption; design and manage IT architecture to ensure consistency and compliance</li>
<li>Chief knowledge officer (CKO) Create knowledge management infrastructure; build a knowledge culture; make corporate knowledge pay off</li>
<li>Chief telecommunications officer (CTO) Manage phones, networks, and other communications technology across entire enterprise</li>
<li>Chief network officer (CNO) Build and maintain internal and external networks</li>
<li>Chief resource officer (CRO) Manage outsourcing relationships</li>
<li>Chief information security officer (CISO) Ensure information management practices are consistent with security requirements</li>
<li>Chief privacy officer (CPO) Be responsible for processes and practices that ensure privacy concerns of customers, employees, and vendors are met</li>
<li>Chief mobility officer (CMO) Oversee and ensure the viable use of the mobile platforms and apps</li>
<li>Chief social media officer (CSMO) Maintain a social IT perspective that results in effectively implementing social media</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="http://pompeiiconsulting.com/strategic-value-of-information-technology">Strategic Value of Information Technology</a></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Otis Elevator Case Study]]></title><description><![CDATA[Customer Relationship Management | IT Consulting | IT Management | Information Technology Consulting | Pompeii Consulting]]></description><link>http://localhost:2368/otis-information-technology-crm/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">708a9f0b-cac7-462d-91cb-bcbf4b58e806</guid><category><![CDATA[information technolog]]></category><category><![CDATA[supply chain management]]></category><category><![CDATA[customer relationship management]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Pompeii Consulting]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2016 00:05:09 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>Focuses on a major transformation of Otis Elevator's infrastructure. Led by the CEO, this transformation represents a remarkable long-term reengineering of all the processes of the firm to drive its operating costs down and service image up. The transformation is the continuation of a process that has been going on for more than 20 years.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://hbr.org/product/otis-elevator-accelerating-business-transformation-with-it/305048-PDF-ENG" target="_blank">Harvard Business Review</a></p>

<p>The IT tools being used by Otis in 2004 were simple – database, workflow software, Intranets and Extranets, email – but the benefits appeared to be extraordinary. What are the things that really had changed in the company over the last few years leading up to 2005?</p>

<p>Otis Elevator’s earliest initiatives had been to build the business through massive acquisitions. Through these acquisitions, Otis was able to expand its customer base extensively and became the “largest manufacturer, installer, and servicer of elevators, escalators, and moving walkways in the world.”    While these acquisitions had been extremely profitable, Otis leadership knew that without consolidation and standardization of products and services within the company, that continued profitability would not be sustainable. </p>

<p>In the years leading up to 2005, Otis leadership recognized their business strategy needed to shift to compare to benchmark companies like UPS who had institutionalized customer service, and developed standardized  workflow processes and metrics to govern every customer interaction and internal activity. The vision moving forward was to become the recognized leader in service excellence among all companies – not just elevator companies – worldwide.</p>

<p>In order to align the  new vision with its business strategy, Otis needed to reduce the number of modules in use and lower project costs.  The SIMBA program was introduced to “fundamentally change the architecture and ultimately the design process; the goal was a standard-interface, modular-based architecture defining modules and subsystems from which all Otis elevator systems could be created.”  Also introduced with the SIMBA program was standard terminology. In the past, Otis verbiage varied so much throughout the organization that communications within the company could be misconstrued or misinterpreted. Through the implementation of a standardized terminology, important concepts such as “contracts, proposals, projects and field modules” would have the same meaning to any party requiring information as to the status of one of these steps in the development or implementation phase. </p>

<p>Tony Black of Otis Field Operations shared the “e-Logistics program which is based on the maturity of SIP.  If we hadn’t done SIP, and just did the e-Logistics program, it would have taken much longer.”   In sum,  Otis Elevator was no longer an “old-line can’t miss industrial firm, which only needed caretakers” as was the description provided by Tom Wolfe decades earlier. </p>

<p><br></p>

<hr>

<p><br></p>

<p>With the e-Logistics program, best practice from SIP are baked into the company and institutionalized to achieve that continuous transformation. How do the systems that comprise the e-Logistics program bake in an institutionalized best practice?</p>

<p>Implementation of the  e-Logistics information transformation project provided Otis’ IT systems with the resources needed to “facilitate business process re-engineering that was taking place throughout.” This was  accomplished by taking the lessons learned from the initial Sales and Installation Process (SIP), and integrating them into a company-wide IT solution geared toward its evolving business model. The  e-Logistics program was built over a two year timeframe by gathering information from subject matter experts in the fields of “sales, field, and order management along with IT project managers.” By doing this, Otis was able to demonstrate the ideals of Pearlson and Saunders when they wrote, “In an organization that operates successfully, an overriding business strategy drives both organizational strategy and information strategy.”  </p>

<p>From an organizational perspective, the Project Proposal phase used a mandatory electronic pre-bid checklist which had to be approved by both the sales representative and the field-installation supervisor. Prior to e-Logistics, this was a manual process, and often times the field-installation supervisor did not even see the checklist or know the requirements until it was time for install.  Instituting this pre-bid checklist ensured the sales and field organizations worked together from the beginning of the process, increased process cohesion and allowed for minimal delays at install.  From an IS perspective, former manual systems, such as booking, validation and scheduling, became centrally automated.  This allowed for the e-Logistics software to automatically push data to appropriate supervisory and financial personnel.  Automated information sharing ensures each  party receives information  efficiently and decreases the need for middle  management. </p>

<p>The Order Fulfillment phase is another example of institutionalization, as field-installation supervisors were responsible for relaying when job sites were ready for deliveries.  The automated email service within e-Logistics prompts supervisors to check in on sites,  allows for status updates and face-to-face interactions with contractors.  This demonstrates how e-Logistics institutionalized site preparation, allowing for the implementation of the “pull” system.  Otis’ Tony Black said that the automated email and reminder process, “forces critical steps of SIP and makes good process part of the way you do business.”</p>

<p>By taking best practices from SIP and integrating them into the automated, e-Logistics program, it ensured both present and future Otis employees would execute these best practices.  This institutionalized, “baked in” program prevents best practices from being lost in two ways: 1) Mandatory use for nearly all employees, which helped Otis move away from many inefficient  manual processes and 2) best practices were now being held within the program, preventing an individual leaving the company and taking job-specific or institutional knowledge with them.  </p>

<p><a href="http://pompeiiconsulting.com/strategic-value-of-information-technology">Strategic Value of Information Technology</a></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Productivity Analysis]]></title><description><![CDATA[Productivity Analysis | Productivity Growth | Efficiency Change | Technical Change | IT Consulting | IT Management | Pompeii Consulting
]]></description><link>http://localhost:2368/business-information-technology-productivity-analysis/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">755bbe7e-5fbc-4616-b710-dc18c2e3e89d</guid><category><![CDATA[information technology]]></category><category><![CDATA[productivity analysis]]></category><category><![CDATA[productivity]]></category><category><![CDATA[efficiency]]></category><category><![CDATA[productivity growth]]></category><category><![CDATA[efficiency change]]></category><category><![CDATA[technical change]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Pompeii Consulting]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2016 00:35:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3 id="performanceevaluation">Performance Evaluation</h3>

<p>"You can't manage what you can't measure." 
- Peter Ducker
<br>  </p>

<h4 id="productivity">Productivity</h4>

<p>productivity = output produced / input consumed</p>

<ul>
<li>always a rational number, 0 &lt;= p &lt; ∞</li>
</ul>

<h5 id="productivitygrowth">Productivity Growth</h5>

<p>productivity growth = productivity at t+1 / productivity at t</p>

<ul>
<li>always an index, 0 &lt;= pg &lt;= 1</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="efficiency">Efficiency</h4>

<p>efficiency = output produced / output maximum </p>

<ul>
<li>aways a ratio or percentage, 0 &lt;= e &lt; 1</li>
</ul>

<h5 id="efficiencychange">Efficiency Change</h5>

<p>efficiency change = efficiency at t+1 / efficiency at t</p>

<ul>
<li>always an index, 0 &lt;= ec &lt;= 1</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="technicalchange">Technical Change</h4>

<p>Production frontier is the line that specifies the ideal maximum output produced at any input level</p>

<p>technical change = slope of production frontier at t+1 / slope of production frontier at t</p>

<ul>
<li>always an index,  0 &lt;= pf &lt;= 1</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="productivitygrowthefficiencychangetechnicalchange">Productivity Growth = Efficiency Change * Technical Change</h4>

<p><br>  </p>

<h3 id="productivityanalysis">Productivity Analysis</h3>

<ul>
<li>Information technology and business management need to know how effectively and efficiently activities are being performed</li>
<li>effectiveness: do the right thing</li>
<li>efficiency: the the thing right</li>
<li>the ability to measure and compare information technology activities</li>
<li>gauge how well information technology is performing</li>
<li>see if information technology is meeting the demands of the firm</li>
<li>challenge is choosing what and when to measure</li>
<li>monitor and control information technology activities</li>
<li>improve performance and demonstrate information technology value</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="http://pompeiiconsulting.com/strategic-value-of-information-technology">Strategic Value of Information Technology</a></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[IT and Business Organization Strategy]]></title><description><![CDATA[Telecommuting | Virtual Teams | Organizational Structures | IT Consulting | IT Management | Pompeii Consulting]]></description><link>http://localhost:2368/information-technology-business-organization-strategy/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6f889599-1c69-4f14-be00-8ddca9651424</guid><category><![CDATA[organizational strategy]]></category><category><![CDATA[data mining]]></category><category><![CDATA[electronic collaboration]]></category><category><![CDATA[organizational structures]]></category><category><![CDATA[networked organization]]></category><category><![CDATA[telecommuting]]></category><category><![CDATA[data collection]]></category><category><![CDATA[virtual teams]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Pompeii Consulting]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2016 23:40:57 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3 id="organizationalstrategy">Organizational Strategy</h3>

<ul>
<li>Organization's design and work processes</li>
<li>Optimize organizational design</li>
<li>Optimize management control systems</li>
<li>Organization structure is the way of designing an organization so decision rights are correctly allocated.</li>
<li>The structure of reporting relationships reflects the flow of communication and decision making in an organization.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="organizationalstructures">Organizational Structures</h3>

<h4 id="hierarchicalorganizationalstructure">Hierarchical Organizational Structure</h4>

<ul>
<li>Description: Bureaucratic with defined levels of management</li>
<li>Characteristics: Division of labor specialization, unity of command</li>
<li>Best Environment: Stable Certain</li>
<li>Basis of Structure: Primary function</li>
<li>Power Structure: Centralized</li>
<li>Key Supporting Technology: Mainframe, centralized data and processing</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="flatorganizationalstructure">Flat Organizational Structure</h4>

<ul>
<li>Description: Decision-making pushed down to lowest level</li>
<li>Characteristics: Informal roles, planning and control; often small, young organizations</li>
<li>Best Environment: Unstable Uncertain</li>
<li>Basis of Structure: Primary function</li>
<li>Power Structure: Centralized</li>
<li>Key Supporting Technology: Personal computers</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="matrixorganizationalstructure">Matrix Organizational Structure</h4>

<ul>
<li>Description: Workers assigned to two or more supervisors</li>
<li>Characteristics: Dual reporting based on function/purpose</li>
<li>Best Environment: Unstable Uncertain</li>
<li>Basis of Structure: Functions and purpose</li>
<li>Power Structure: Distributed</li>
<li>Key Supporting Technology: Networks</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="networkedorganizationalstructure">Networked Organizational Structure</h4>

<ul>
<li>Description: Formal/informal communication networks that connect all</li>
<li>Characteristics: Known for flexibility and adaptability</li>
<li>Best Environment: Unstable Uncertain</li>
<li>Basis of Structure: Networks</li>
<li>Power Structure: Distributed</li>
<li>Key Supporting Technology: Intranets and Internet</li>
<li>Employees share their knowledge and experience,and participate in making key organizational decisions.</li>
<li>Information Systems are fundamental to process design, improve process efficiency, effectiveness, and flexibility.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="informalnetworks">Informal Networks</h3>

<h4 id="informalrelationshipsdesignatedbymanagement">Informal Relationships designated by management</h4>

<ul>
<li>working on a project</li>
<li>job rotation program</li>
<li>call upon past co-workers</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="unintendednetworks">Unintended Networks</h4>

<ul>
<li>work proximity</li>
<li>shared interests</li>
<li>family ties</li>
<li>politics crossing organizations</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="socialnetworking">Social Networking</h4>

<ul>
<li>links individuals together</li>
<li>find experts</li>
<li>meet colleges</li>
<li>find relevant experience</li>
<li>crosses traditional organizations</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="managementcontrol">Management Control</h3>

<ul>
<li>Information technology affects how managers control their organizations</li>
<li>Management control systems respond to goals established through planning</li>
<li>Goals are periodically adjusted</li>
<li>Control work at process level</li>
<li>Organizational structure will dictate level of managerial control</li>
<li>Information Systems in Management Control Processes:
<ul><li>data collection</li>
<li>evaluation</li>
<li>communication</li></ul></li>
<li>Gives management more time to make decisions</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="datacollectionandinformationtechnology">Data Collection and Information Technology</h3>

<p>Monitoring work using information technology</p>

<ul>
<li>keystrokes</li>
<li>time spent on a task</li>
<li>who is contacted </li>
</ul>

<h4 id="organizationaldesignchallengesindatacollection">Organizational design challenges in data collection</h4>

<ul>
<li>embedded monitoring tasks within everyday work</li>
<li>reduce the negative impacts to monitored workers</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="datacollectionsoftware">Data collection software</h4>

<ul>
<li>can backfire, cause stress</li>
<li>used to reward, not just punish</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="evaluationandinformationtechnology">Evaluation and Information Technology</h3>

<ul>
<li>Information Technology enables evaluating against standard data and historical data</li>
<li>models can be built</li>
<li>simulations designed</li>
<li>managers can easily understand work progress and performance</li>
<li>analysis paralysis: too much data or information</li>
<li>how feedback is communicated effects behavior</li>
<li>information handled discreetly and appropriately</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="incentivesandrewardandinformationtechnology">Incentives and Reward and Information Technology</h3>

<ul>
<li>ways to incentivize good performance</li>
<li>can make employees feel good and boost morale</li>
<li>use websites to recognize high performers</li>
<li>reward with new technology</li>
<li>Information Technology allows for complex reward systems, shared and team based</li>
<li>consider metrics and qualitative data in assigning compensation and rewards</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="informationsystemsandculture">Information Systems and Culture</h3>

<ul>
<li>culture is one managerial lever </li>
<li>set of values and beliefs about what is desirable and undesirable in a community of people</li>
<li>culture is always changing</li>
<li>national culture differences effect information systems development and use</li>
<li>understand and appreciate cultural values, practices, and subtleties</li>
<li>improve communications and reduce conflict</li>
<li>listening, framing, and responding to feedback</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="informationtechnologyandvirtualorganization">Information Technology and Virtual Organization</h3>

<ul>
<li>time and place of work blended</li>
<li>can do work at home, own own time</li>
<li>virtual organization is a networked structure that makes it possible for individuals to work and live anywhere</li>
<li>internet and corporate intranets create the opportunity for individuals to work from anywhere</li>
<li>virtual organizations depend upon collaboration</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="workdesignframework">Work Design Framework</h3>

<p>Used to asses how emerging information technology affects work</p>

<ul>
<li>What work will be performed?</li>
<li>Who is going to do the work?</li>
<li>Where will the work be performed?</li>
<li>When will the work be performed?</li>
<li>How can information technology increase the effectiveness of the workers doing the work?</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="informationtechnologytofacilitatecommunication">Information Technology to Facilitate Communication</h3>

<ul>
<li>email</li>
<li>intranet</li>
<li>instant messaging (IM)</li>
<li>Voice over IP (VoIP)</li>
<li>Video Teleconferencing</li>
<li>Unified Communications (UC)</li>
<li>Really Simple Syndication (RSS)</li>
<li>Virtual Private Network (VPN)</li>
<li>File Transfer</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="informationtechnologytofacilitatecollaboration">Information Technology to Facilitate Collaboration</h3>

<ul>
<li>social networking</li>
<li>virtual worlds</li>
<li>web logs (blogs)</li>
<li>wikis</li>
<li>groupware</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="informationtechnologychangesnatureofwork">Information Technology Changes Nature of Work</h3>

<ul>
<li>creates many new jobs</li>
<li>redefines existing ones
<ul><li>the way work is done</li>
<li>communication patterns</li>
<li>organizational decision making</li>
<li>information processing</li>
<li>collaboration</li>
<li>ways to connect</li></ul></li>
<li>how to manage workforce
<ul><li>supervising</li>
<li>evaluating</li>
<li>rewarding</li>
<li>hiring</li></ul></li>
<li>careers
<ul><li>programers</li>
<li>business analysts</li>
<li>information technology managers</li>
<li>hardware assemblers</li>
<li>web site designers</li>
<li>softwares sales personnel</li>
<li>information technology consultants</li></ul></li>
</ul>

<h4 id="traditionalsubjectiveobservation">Traditional: Subjective Observation</h4>

<ul>
<li>Supervision: Personal and informal. Manager is usually present or relies on others to ensure that employee is present and productive.</li>
<li>Evaluation: Focus is on process through direct observation. Manager sees how employee performed at work. Subjective (personal) factors are very important.</li>
<li>Compensation: Often individually-based.</li>
<li>Hiring: Personal with little reliance on computers. Often more reliance on clerical skills.</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="modernobjectiveobservation">Modern: Objective Observation</h4>

<ul>
<li>Supervision: Electronic or assessed by deliverable. As long as the employee is producing value, he does not need formal supervisions.</li>
<li>Evaluation: Focus is on output by deliverable (e.g., produce a report by a certain date) or by target (e.g., meet a sales quota). As long as deliverables are produced and/or targets are achieved, the employee is meeting performance expectations adequately. Subjective factors may be less important and harder to gauge.</li>
<li>Compensation: Often team-based or contractually spelled out.</li>
<li>Hiring: Often electronic with recruiting websites and electronic testing. More information- based work that requires a higher level of IT skills.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="telecommuting">Telecommuting</h3>

<ul>
<li>Started in 1970's</li>
<li>Gained popularity in late 1990's</li>
<li>reduces stress</li>
<li>geographic flexibility</li>
<li>higher productivity</li>
<li>tapping housebound individuals</li>
<li>difficult for managers to evaluate performance</li>
<li>workers must be extremely self disciplined</li>
<li>may end up working more hours</li>
<li>can be disconnected from corporate culture</li>
<li>offshoring enabled by same technology</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="managerialissuesintelecommuting">Managerial Issues in Telecommuting</h4>

<ul>
<li>planning, business, and support tasks must be redesigned to support mobile and remote workers</li>
<li>training should be offered so all workers understand the new work environment</li>
<li>employees must be self starters</li>
<li>managers must fined new ways to evaluate and supervise employees without seeing them everyday</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="virtualteams">Virtual Teams</h4>

<p>Geographically or organizationally dispersed coworkers assembled using information technology and telecommunications</p>

<ul>
<li>same drivers as telecommuting</li>
<li>teams in different parts of the world can cooperate
<ul><li>get jobs done faster</li>
<li>around the clock</li></ul></li>
<li>different time zones</li>
<li>security is harder to ensure</li>
<li>lose nuances of face to face conversation</li>
<li>trust may be slower to form</li>
<li>diversity of team members
<ul><li>language</li>
<li>culture</li>
<li>customs</li></ul></li>
</ul>

<h4 id="lifecycleofvirtualteams">Life Cycle of Virtual Teams</h4>

<h5 id="preparation">Preparation</h5>

<ul>
<li>mission statement</li>
<li>personnel selection</li>
<li>task design</li>
<li>rewards sustem</li>
<li>technology selection</li>
<li>technology installment</li>
</ul>

<h5 id="launch">Launch</h5>

<ul>
<li>kickoff meetings</li>
<li>getting acquainted</li>
<li>goal clarification</li>
<li>norm development</li>
</ul>

<h5 id="performancemanagement">Performance Management</h5>

<ul>
<li>leadership</li>
<li>communication</li>
<li>conflict resolution</li>
<li>task accomplishment</li>
<li>motivation</li>
<li>knowledge management</li>
<li>norm enforcement</li>
<li>norm shaping</li>
</ul>

<h5 id="teamdevelopment">Team Development</h5>

<ul>
<li>assessment of needs and deficits</li>
<li>individual or team training</li>
<li>evaluation of training effects</li>
<li>trust building</li>
</ul>

<h5 id="disbanding">Disbanding</h5>

<ul>
<li>recognition of achievements</li>
<li>reintegration of team members</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="managerialissuesinvirtualteams">Managerial Issues in Virtual Teams</h4>

<ul>
<li>require different style and type of management</li>
<li>observation is less likely to occur</li>
<li>performance is more likely to be based on output</li>
<li>providing feedback is important</li>
<li>compensation should be based on team performance</li>
<li>align rewards with achievement of team goals</li>
<li>challenges
<ul><li>communication</li>
<li>technology</li>
<li>diversity</li></ul></li>
</ul>

<h3 id="informationtechnologyinducedchange">Information Technology Induced Change</h3>

<ul>
<li>in order to avoid resistance to change, must actively manage the change process</li>
<li>employee attitudes may change if perception of new system is it helps them do more work, better work for the same or less effort, and it is easy to use</li>
<li>employee participation in system design and implementation</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="technologyacceptancemodel">Technology Acceptance Model</h3>

<ul>
<li>Individual Differences</li>
<li>System Characteristics</li>
<li>Social Influence</li>
<li>Facilitating Conditions</li>
</ul>

<p>Technology Acceptance Model (TAM)</p>

<ul>
<li>Perceived Usefulness</li>
<li>Perceived Ease of Use
<ul><li>Behavioral Intention</li>
<li>Use Behavior</li></ul></li>
</ul>

<p><a href="http://pompeiiconsulting.com/strategic-value-of-information-technology">Strategic Value of Information Technology</a></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Strategy and the Internet]]></title><description><![CDATA[Internet Business |Competitive Advantage IT Consulting | IT Management | Information Technology Consulting | Pompeii Consulting]]></description><link>http://localhost:2368/competitive-advantage-internet/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">8fd2b1bf-5275-45ae-9ede-462e05540e77</guid><category><![CDATA[business strategy]]></category><category><![CDATA[information technology]]></category><category><![CDATA[information management]]></category><category><![CDATA[competitive advantage]]></category><category><![CDATA[internet]]></category><category><![CDATA[disruptive innovation]]></category><category><![CDATA[information strategy]]></category><category><![CDATA[organizational strategy]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Pompeii Consulting]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2016 18:34:20 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>Many of the pioneers of Internet business, both dot-coms and established companies, have competed in ways that violate nearly every precept of good strategy. Rather than focus on profits, they have chased customers indiscriminately through discounting, channel incentives, and advertising. Rather than concentrate on delivering value that earns an attractive price from customers, they have pursued indirect revenues such as advertising and click-through fees. Rather than make trade-offs, they have rushed to offer every conceivable product or service. It did not have to be this way--and it does not have to be in the future. When it comes to reinforcing a distinctive strategy, Michael Porter argues, the Internet provides a better technological platform than previous generations of IT. Gaining competitive advantage does not require a radically new approach to business; it requires building on the proven principles of effective strategy. Porter argues that, contrary to recent thought, the Internet is not disruptive to most existing industries and established companies. It rarely nullifies important sources of competitive advantage in an industry; it often makes them even more valuable. And as all companies embrace Internet technology, the Internet itself will be neutralized as a source of advantage. Robust competitive advantages will arise instead from traditional strengths such as unique products, proprietary content, and distinctive physical activities. Internet technology may be able to fortify those advantages, but it is unlikely to supplant them.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://hbr.org/product/strategy-and-the-internet/R0103D-PDF-ENG" target="_blank">Harvard Business Review</a></p>

<p>Why isn’t a business strategy sufficient for a company to determine how it can leverage IT for competitive advantage? Based on the descriptions of "Strategy and the Internet", how would you characterize Walgreens’ business strategy and IS strategy in using the Internet for its business?</p>

<p>Business strategy alone is not sufficient for a company to determine how it can leverage IT for competitive advantage. As stated in the IS Strategy Triangle slide, “companies are said to be in alignment when their business strategy is supported/enabled/driven by their information strategy.” The business strategy must be adhered to first and foremost with the organizational and information strategy supporting and aligning with it. In order to achieve a sustainable competitive advantage, the business needs “to be more profitable than the average performer,” according to the Strategy and the Internet article. The article further indicates that operational effectiveness, and strategic positioning are key drivers for competitive advantage. Business strategy and IT both come with their own strengths.  In Managing and Using Information Systems, the author states that “IS and business maturity must be aligned to provide the right level of information resources to the business.” It is imperative that IT be leveraged as a participant in the overall business strategy, but sustainability and profitability need to be the key drivers. <br>
Walgreens’ business and IS strategy can be characterized as a two-pronged model for success. By integrating the internet (i.e. online ordering services), rather than cannibalizing or forfeiting their established core business strategy (brick and mortar stores), the company was able to increase the success of its existing business model through the use of a complementary arrangement between the two channels. Walgreens embraced the ideals from the article that stated, “Established companies will be most successful when they deploy Internet technology to reconfigure traditional activities or when they find new combinations of Internet and traditional approaches.” This ideal allowed them to reach a larger, more diverse customer base, while continuing to satisfy its existing one. <br>
<br></p>

<hr>

<p><br> <br>
Use the Porter’s 5 competitive forces model, perform an analysis similar to the one by Porter on pages 5-7 in “Strategy and the Internet,” and predict how the phenomena of Web 2.0 like social networking would influence industry structure and profitability for an average firm?</p>

<h3 id="threatofnewentrants">Threat of New Entrants</h3>

<p>(-) “Sharing economy” has drastically reduced the barriers to entry for service work, both on-site and remote. (-) Lower barrier to entry for products, ideas can be shared and go viral over social media. (-) Crowdfunding, such as Kickstarter reduce capital requirements for entrants into a product category. (+) Synergy between established physical locations and mobile, such as grubhub and postmates, adds value to existing infrastructure.</p>

<h3 id="bargainingpowerofbuyers">Bargaining Power of Buyers</h3>

<p>(-) Bargaining power of end user increases due to ease and availability of information about new, alternative, and rival products. (-) Buyers can insinuate a bidding war, by having firms compete on price (-) Buyers have drastically increased power and voice due to social media, with a tweet can become a national headline. (+) Happy and vocal customers with clout on social media can advocate for a firm, for free or through sponsorship.</p>

<h3 id="bargainingpowerofsuppliers">Bargaining Power of Suppliers</h3>

<p>(+) Sites and platforms such as Alibaba and SalesForce allow for more choice and alternatives when a firm is selecting a supplier for a product or service that can increase fit and thus efficiency. (+) “Sharing Economy” has allowed for an alternative to some services, à la carte and in a reliable fashion; less overhead, more flexibility. (-) Suppliers, of both goods and services, can more easily go direct to market, bypassing the firm.</p>

<h3 id="threatofsubstitutes">Threat of Substitutes</h3>

<p>(-) Social/viral advertising allows for alternative products to gain consumer mind share more easily than before. (-) Mobile allows for substitute products to be found not just at home but from nearly anywhere, even in a firm’s retail location. (-) “Sharing economy” has allowed easy competition on the services side, creating alternatives that never existed before. (+) Social engagement and brand recognition can help buffer against new entrants, by forming a relationship with customers.</p>

<h3 id="industrycompetitors">Industry Competitors</h3>

<p>(-) Social engagement with customers is mandatory order to stay relevant and competitive to others in the industry. (-) Reduced competitive advantages in organizational systems as SaaS’s such as SalesForce continue to dominate the market. (+) Increased similarities in organizational systems can increase the ease of acquisitions.</p>

<p><a href="http://pompeiiconsulting.com/strategic-value-of-information-technology">Strategic Value of Information Technology</a></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Business Basics]]></title><description><![CDATA[Economics | IT Consulting | IT Management | Information Technology Consulting | Information Technology Management | Pompeii Consulting]]></description><link>http://localhost:2368/business-information-technology/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6cd6b498-0442-4aac-8bf0-d821ab5f821e</guid><category><![CDATA[business]]></category><category><![CDATA[profit]]></category><category><![CDATA[law of demand]]></category><category><![CDATA[law of supply]]></category><category><![CDATA[network effect]]></category><category><![CDATA[economics]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Pompeii Consulting]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2016 22:17:09 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>It is not from the benevolence of the butcher, the brewer, or the baker, that we expect our dinner, but from their regard to their own interest</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Adam Smith, <em>The Wealth of Nations</em></p>

<p>Businesses try to maximize profit <br>
Profit, net income, net earnings, bottom line (of income statement)</p>

<p>Profit = Total Revenues - Total Costs <br>
Profit = (Price x Quantity) - (Total Fixed Costs + Total Variable Costs)</p>

<p>To increase profit</p>

<ul>
<li>increase total revenue
<ul><li>increase price</li>
<li>increase quantity</li></ul></li>
<li>decrease total costs
<ul><li>decrease fixed costs</li>
<li>decrease variable costs</li></ul></li>
</ul>

<h3 id="lawofdemand">Law of Demand</h3>

<p>Inverse relationship between price and quantity</p>

<h4 id="demandsideeconomiesofscale">Demand Side Economies of Scale</h4>

<p>Violates the Law of Demand</p>

<ul>
<li>Luxury Goods: as price increases so does quantity
<ul><li>Rolex, Gucci</li></ul></li>
<li>Network Goods: as quantity increases so does price
<ul><li>Microsoft Office, Skype, Facebook</li></ul></li>
</ul>

<h3 id="supplysideeconomics">Supply Side Economics</h3>

<p>Desire to decrease average fixed cost and average variable cost</p>

<h4 id="supplysideeconomiesofscale">Supply Side Economies of Scale</h4>

<p>Increase quantity leads to a decrease in average costs</p>

<ul>
<li>Average Fixed Costs = Total Fixed Costs / Quantity
<ul><li>Fixed cost leverage</li></ul></li>
<li>Average Variable Costs = Total Variable Costs / Quantity
<ul><li>volume discount, learning effect, division of labor</li></ul></li>
</ul>

<h3 id="maximizeprofit">Maximize Profit</h3>

<p>Marginal Revenues = Marginal Costs</p>

<h3 id="informationtechnology">Information Technology</h3>

<h4 id="impactsonprofitability">Impacts on Profitability</h4>

<ul>
<li>Network Effects
<ul><li>Winner take all systems</li></ul></li>
<li>Software
<ul><li>large fixed cost</li>
<li>near zero variable costs</li>
<li>example: freeware</li></ul></li>
<li>Information Technology enhanced learning</li>
<li>Information Technology based transformation of industry structure
<ul><li>example: Netflix vs Blockbuster</li></ul></li>
</ul>

<h3 id="businessethics">Business Ethics</h3>

<ul>
<li>Resources be used efficiently and allocated effectively</li>
<li>Greatest economic value can be created</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="http://pompeiiconsulting.com/strategic-value-of-information-technology">Strategic Value of Information Technology</a></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Strategic Alignment]]></title><description><![CDATA[IT Strategy | Competitive Advantage | IT Consulting | IT Management | Information Technology Consulting | Pompeii Consulting]]></description><link>http://localhost:2368/strategic-alignment/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">dd62b66a-77c1-40e7-91b2-ad8d6080feb7</guid><category><![CDATA[Harvard Business Review]]></category><category><![CDATA[information systems]]></category><category><![CDATA[competitive advantage]]></category><category><![CDATA[information technology]]></category><category><![CDATA[business strategy]]></category><category><![CDATA[strategic advantage]]></category><category><![CDATA[value chain]]></category><category><![CDATA[Value of IT]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Pompeii Consulting]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2016 22:25:16 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>Many have argued that the Internet renders strategy obsolete. In reality, the opposite is true. Because the Internet tends to weaken industry profitability without providing proprietary operational advantages, it is more important than ever for companies to distinguish themselves through strategy. The winners will be those that view the Internet as a complement to, not a cannibal of, traditional ways of competing.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://hbr.org/product/strategy-and-the-internet/R0103D-PDF-ENG" target="_blank">Harvard Business Review</a></p>

<h3 id="informationsystemsstrategytriangle">Information Systems Strategy Triangle</h3>

<ul>
<li>Business Strategy</li>
<li>Organization Strategy</li>
<li><p>Information Strategy</p></li>
<li><p>Successful when in alignment</p></li>
<li>Overriding business strategy, drive organizational and information strategies</li>
<li>Change in 1 require change in the other 2</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="strategy">Strategy</h4>

<p>coordinated set of actions to fulfill goals, objectives, and purposes; it involves mission and vision.  </p>

<h4 id="businessstrategy">Business Strategy</h4>

<p>plan articulating where a business seeks to go and how it expects to get there.</p>

<h4 id="sustainablecompetitiveadvantage">Sustainable competitive advantage:</h4>

<ul>
<li>cost leadership: lower cost</li>
<li>differentiation: unique product</li>
<li>focus: limited scope</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="hypercompetitionmodelsuggestthatthespeedandmarketdynamicscreateanenvironmentsuchthat">Hyper-competition model suggest that the speed and market dynamics create an environment such that:</h4>

<ul>
<li>every advantage is quickly eroded</li>
<li>sustaining an advantage can be a deadly distraction</li>
<li>goal of advantage should be disruption, not sustainability</li>
<li>initiatives are achieved through series of small steps</li>
<li>GE Destroy Your Business Project</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="strategicadvantagesrelatedtoinformationsystems">Strategic Advantages Related to Information Systems</h3>

<ul>
<li>Managers cannot rely solely on IT to make IT decisions</li>
<li>Business strategy drives Information Systems decisions</li>
<li>Change in Information Systems potential triggers business reassessment
<ul><li>Internet, mobile, social networks</li></ul></li>
</ul>

<p>Framework <br>
Porter's Generic Strategies <br>
Key Idea <br>
Competitive advantage: cost, differentiate, focus <br>
App to Information Systems <br>
Information Systems chosen to match strategy</p>

<p>Famework <br>
Dynamic Environment Strategies <br>
Key Idea <br>
Speed, agility, and aggressive moves and counter moves create competitive advantage <br>
App to Information Systems <br>
Information Systems critical to achieving the required speed of innovation, moves, and counter moves. In a constant state of flux/development.</p>

<h3 id="organizationstrategyframework">Organization Strategy Framework</h3>

<ul>
<li>organization design and choices to make it work processes</li>
<li>How a company organizes to achieve it goals and implement its business strategy</li>
<li>Business Diamond identifies core components of the org's plan.
<ul><li>tasks and structure</li>
<li>management and measurement systems</li>
<li>values and belief</li>
<li>business processes</li></ul></li>
</ul>

<h3 id="managerialleversframework">Managerial Levers Framework</h3>

<ul>
<li>Strategy, Execution, Organizational Effectiveness</li>
<li>Success = organization variables + control variables + culture variables</li>
<li>Organization variables
<ul><li>business processes</li>
<li>formal Reporting relationships</li>
<li>informal networks</li>
<li>decision rights</li></ul></li>
<li>Control variables
<ul><li>decision rights</li>
<li>data</li>
<li>planning </li>
<li>performance measurements and evaluation</li></ul></li>
<li>Culture variables
<ul><li>Values</li>
<li>Incentives and rewards</li></ul></li>
</ul>

<h4 id="informationsystemsstrategy">Information Systems Strategy</h4>

<p>the plan an organization uses to provide information services; helps implement business strategy and determine the company's capabilities</p>

<h4 id="infrastructurecomponents">Infrastructure Components:</h4>

<p>What | Who | Where <br>
Hardware: system components | individual users and managers | physical location <br>
Software: programs, applications, and utilities | individuals and managers | hardware it is on an that hardwares location <br>
Networking: Diagram of connection between hardware and software | individuals, managers, and company from | nodes, wires, and other media location <br>
Data: Bits of information in system | individuals and managers | information is stored</p>

<h4 id="erasofinformationusage">Eras of Information Usage</h4>

<p>Role of IT | Justification | Target | Models <br>
Technology | Basis | Economics <br>
60's <br>
Efficiency | ROI | Organization | Application <br>
Mainframe | Scarcity | Bundled <br>
70's <br>
Effectiveness | Productivity| Organization &amp; Group | Data <br>
Minicomputers| Scarcity | Bundled <br>
80's <br>
Strategic | Competitive | Individual &amp; Group | User <br>
Microcomputers | Scarcity | Bundled <br>
1990's <br>
Strategic/Transform | Competitive | Business Process | Business <br>
Client-Server | Plentitude | Separated <br>
2000's <br>
Value &amp; Partnership | Adding Value | Customer/Supplier | Knowledge <br>
Internet | Plentitude | Separated <br>
2010's <br>
Community &amp; Social | Relationships | Customer/Employee | People <br>
Social, Mobile , Cloud | Plentitude | Relationships Bundled</p>

<p>Data -> Information -> Knowledge -> Intelligence -> Data</p>

<p>Information Resources: data, technology, people, and processes available to perform business processes and tasks <br>
Move from efficiency model to value creation model</p>

<h4 id="informationtechnologyasset">Information Technology Asset:</h4>

<p>Thing or idea used in creating, producing, and offering a product</p>

<ul>
<li>Information Technology Infrastructure: Hardware, software, network, data components, proprietary technology, web-based services</li>
<li>Information Repository: Critical information about customers that can be used to gain strategic advantage. Much of this information is increasingly available on the web</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="informationtechnologycapability">Information Technology Capability:</h4>

<p>Learned or developed over time to create, produce, or offer a product</p>

<ul>
<li>Technical Skill: Proficiency in systems analysis and design; programming skills</li>
<li>IT Management Skills: Being knowledgeable about business processes and managing systems to support them; evaluating technology options; envisioning creative Information Systems solutions to business problems</li>
<li>Relationship Skills: having a good relationship between IT and business managers; have a good relationship with an outsourcing vendor</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="valueofinformationresources">Value of Information Resources</h3>

<p>Network Effect: Value of a network node increases to a person or organization when others join the network. Rather than production cost (close to zero), valued is calculated as value to the buyer, which increases along with the size of the network.</p>

<h3 id="thestrategiclandscape">The Strategic Landscape</h3>

<ul>
<li>Managers confront elements that influence the competitive environment</li>
<li>Slim tolerance for error</li>
<li>Managers must take multiple views of the strategic landscape
<ul><li>External: Porter's 5 Forces model</li>
<li>Internal:Porter's Value Chain model</li>
<li>Resource-Based: Identify types of Information Systems resources and capabilities needed</li></ul></li>
</ul>

<h3 id="portersfiveforcesmodel">Porter's Five Forces Model:</h3>

<p>Shape external competitive environment</p>

<ul>
<li>Threat of New Entrants
<ul><li>switching costs</li>
<li>access to distribution channels</li>
<li>economies of scale</li></ul></li>
<li>Bargaining Power of Buyers
<ul><li>buyer selection</li>
<li>switching costs</li>
<li>differentiation</li></ul></li>
<li>Bargaining Power of Suppliers
<ul><li>selection of supplier</li>
<li>threat of backward integration</li></ul></li>
<li>Threat of Substitutes (equivalent or superior alternative)
<ul><li>redefine products and services</li>
<li>improve price/performance</li></ul></li>
<li>Industry Competitors
<ul><li>cost-effectiveness</li>
<li>market access</li>
<li>differentiation of product/service</li></ul></li>
</ul>

<h3 id="portersvaluechainmodel">Porter's Value Chain Model:</h3>

<p>Internal activities that crate, deliver, and support products and services</p>

<h4 id="primaryactivities">Primary Activities:</h4>

<p>relates directly to the value created in a product or service</p>

<ul>
<li>Inbound Logistics</li>
<li>Operations</li>
<li>Outbound Logistics</li>
<li>Marketing and Sales</li>
<li>Service </li>
</ul>

<h4 id="supportactivities">Support Activities:</h4>

<p>make it possible for the primary activities to exist and remain coordinated</p>

<ul>
<li>Organization</li>
<li>Human Resources</li>
<li>Technology</li>
<li>Purchasing</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="valuechainsystem">Value Chain System</h3>

<p>Advantage comes from understanding how information is used within and across the value chains in the system <br>
ex: supply chain management (SCM) <br>
supplier value chain -> firm value chain -> channel value chain -> buyer value chain</p>

<h3 id="resourcebasedviewrbv">Resource-Based View (RBV)</h3>

<p>Gain competitive advantage through the use of information resources</p>

<ul>
<li>Attain Competitive Advantage: rare and valuable</li>
<li>Sustain Competitive Advantage: difficult to substitute, imitate, and relatively immobile</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="potentialrisks">Potential Risks</h3>

<ul>
<li>Awakening Sleeping Giant: large competitor with more capital incentives to implement Information Systems</li>
<li>Demonstrating bad timing: customers not ready for new technology</li>
<li>Poor Information Systems implementation</li>
<li>Failing to deliver firms target, usually fail</li>
<li>Web-based alternative removes advantages</li>
<li>Running afoul of the law</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="cocreatinginformationtechnologyandbusinessstrategy">Co-Creating Information Technology and Business Strategy</h3>

<ul>
<li>Information core component of product or service offered by firms</li>
<li>Information Technology strategy should enable and drive business strategy: co-created</li>
<li>High Information Technology and Business strategic alignment</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="strategyandtheinternet">Strategy and the Internet</h2>

<p>Two factors determine profitability</p>

<ul>
<li>industry structure</li>
<li>sustainable competitive advantage</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="howtheinternetinfluenceindustrystructure">How the Internet Influence Industry Structure</h3>

<h4 id="threatofsubstituteproductsorservices">Threat of substitute products or services</h4>

<ul>
<li>(+) By making the overall industry more efficient, the Internet can expand the size of the market</li>
<li>(-) The proliferation of Internet approaches creates new substitution threats</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="bargainingpowerbargainingpowerofsuppliers">Bargaining power Bargaining power of Suppliers</h4>

<ul>
<li>(+/-) Procurement using the Internet tends to raise bargaining power over suppliers, though it can also give suppliers access to more customers</li>
<li>(-) The Internet provides a channel for suppliers to reach end users, reducing the leverage of intervening companies</li>
<li>(-) Internet procurement and digital markets tend to give all companies equal access to suppliers, and gravitate procurement to standardized products that
reduce differentiation  </li>
<li>(-) Reduced barriers to entry and the proliferation of competitors downstream shifts power to suppliers</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="rivalryamongexistingcompetitors">Rivalry among existing competitors</h4>

<ul>
<li>(-) Reduces differences among competitors as offerings are difficult to keep proprietary</li>
<li>(-) Migrates competition to price</li>
<li>(-) Widens the geographic market, increasing the number of competitors</li>
<li>(-) Lowers variable cost relative to fixed cost, increasing pressures for price discounting</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="buyers">Buyers</h4>

<h5 id="bargainingpowerofchannels">Bargaining power of channels</h5>

<ul>
<li>(+) Eliminates powerful
channels or improves bargaining power over traditional channels</li>
</ul>

<h5 id="bargainingpowerofendusers">Bargaining power of end users</h5>

<ul>
<li>(-) Shifts bargaining power to end consumers</li>
<li>(-) Reduces switching costs</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="barrierstoentry">Barriers to Entry</h4>

<ul>
<li>(-) Reduces barriers to entry such as the need for a sales force, access to channels, and physical assets – anything that Internet technology eliminates or makes easier to do reduces barriers to entry</li>
<li>(-) Internet applications are difficult to keep proprietary from new entrants</li>
<li>(-) A flood of new entrants has come into many industries</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="impactsoftheinternetoncompetitiveadvantage">Impacts of the internet on competitive advantage</h3>

<ul>
<li>operational effectiveness -> competitive convergence</li>
<li>strategic position -> convenience, service, specialization, customization</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="sixprinciplesofstrategicpositioning">Six Principles of Strategic Positioning</h3>

<ul>
<li>right goal</li>
<li>value proposition</li>
<li>distinct value chain</li>
<li>tradeoffs</li>
<li>fit</li>
<li>continuity</li>
</ul>

<p>Internet should complement, not canalize traditional actives <br>
Strategic imperatives for dot-coms vs established companies</p>

<h3 id="prominentapplicationsoftheinternetinthevaluechain">Prominent Applications of the Internet in the Value Chain</h3>

<h4 id="supportactivities">Support Activities</h4>

<h5 id="firminfrastructure">Firm Infrastructure</h5>

<ul>
<li>Web-based, distributed financial and ERP systems</li>
<li>On-line investor relations (e.g., information dissemination, broadcast conference calls)</li>
</ul>

<h5 id="humanresourcemanagement">Human Resource Management</h5>

<ul>
<li>Self-service personnel and benefits administration</li>
<li>Web-based training</li>
<li>Internet-based sharing and dissemination of company information</li>
<li>Electronic time and expense reporting</li>
</ul>

<h5 id="technologydevelopment">Technology Development</h5>

<ul>
<li>Collaborative product design across locations and among multiple value-system participants</li>
<li>Knowledge directories accessible from all parts of the organization</li>
<li>Real-time access by R&amp;D to on-line sales and service information</li>
</ul>

<h5 id="procurement">Procurement</h5>

<ul>
<li>Internet-enabled demand planning; real-time available-to-promise/capable-to-promise and fulfillment</li>
<li>Other linkage of purchase, inventory, and forecasting systems with suppliers</li>
<li>Automated “requisition to pay”</li>
<li>Direct and indirect procurement via marketplaces, exchanges, auctions, and buyer-seller matching</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="primaryactivities">Primary Activities</h4>

<h5 id="inboundlogistics">Inbound Logistics</h5>

<ul>
<li>Real-time integrated scheduling, shipping, warehouse management, demand management and planning, and advanced planning and scheduling across the company and its suppliers</li>
<li>Dissemination throughout the company of real-time inbound and in-progress inventory data</li>
</ul>

<h5 id="operations">Operations</h5>

<ul>
<li>Integrated information exchange, scheduling, and decision making in in-house plants, contract assemblers, and components suppliers</li>
<li>Real-time available-to- promise and capable- to-promise information available to the sales force and channels</li>
</ul>

<h5 id="outboundlogistics">Outbound Logistics</h5>

<ul>
<li>Real-time transaction of orders whether initiated by an end consumer, a sales person, or a channel partner</li>
<li>Automated customer- specific agreements and contract terms</li>
<li>Customer and channel ac- cess to product development and delivery status</li>
<li>Collaborative integration with customer forecasting systems</li>
<li>Integrated channel management including information exchange, warranty claims, and con- tract management (versioning, process control)</li>
</ul>

<h5 id="marketingandsales">Marketing and Sales</h5>

<ul>
<li>On-line sales channels including Web sites and marketplaces</li>
<li>Real-time inside and outside access to customer information, product catalogs, dynamic pricing, inventory availability, on-line submission of quotes, and order entry</li>
<li>On-line product configurators</li>
<li>Customer-tailored market- ing via customer profiling</li>
<li>Push advertising</li>
<li>Tailored on-line access</li>
<li>Real-time customer feed-back through Web surveys, opt-in/opt-out marketing, and promotion response tracking</li>
</ul>

<h5 id="aftersalesservice">After-Sales Service</h5>

<ul>
<li>On-line support of customer service representatives through e-mail response management, billing integration, co- browse, chat, “call me now,” voice-over-IP, and other uses of video streaming</li>
<li>Customer self-service via Web sites and intelligent service request processing including updates to billing and shipping profiles</li>
<li>Real-time field service access to customer account review, schematic review, parts availability and ordering, work-order update, and service parts management</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="http://pompeiiconsulting.com/strategic-value-of-information-technology" target="_blank">Strategic Value of Information Technology</a></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Alibris Case Study]]></title><description><![CDATA[e-Commerce | Software Development | IT Consulting | IT Management | Information Technology Consulting | Pompeii Consulting]]></description><link>http://localhost:2368/e-commerce-case-study/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">40bd1757-1dc8-474b-a87a-3af384a1e089</guid><category><![CDATA[e-commerce]]></category><category><![CDATA[case study]]></category><category><![CDATA[IT Management]]></category><category><![CDATA[software development]]></category><category><![CDATA[Amazon.com]]></category><category><![CDATA[Harvard Business Review]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Pompeii Consulting]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 14 Aug 2016 17:02:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<style>  
table, th, td {  
    border: 1px solid black;
}
</style>

<blockquote>
  <p>Alibris is an Internet-era company providing search and fulfillment services for hard-to-find (rare, used, and out-of-print) books. At the time of the case, the company had made decisions to change its revenue model, to become involved in the fulfillment process for each book it sells by establishing a cross-dock facility, and to purchase Oracle's Internet commerce software. However, the implementation of this software has been very difficult, delaying the launch of the new fulfillment business and costing large amounts of money at a time when cash is scarce. The company's leaders, who are not IT professionals, must decide whether to continue with Oracle or begin anew with another product.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://hbr.org/product/alibris-a/601111-PDF-ENG" target="_blank">Harvard Business Review</a></p>

<h2 id="exercise1">Exercise 1</h2>

<h3 id="assumptions">Assumptions</h3>

<ul>
<li>Technology is easy</li>
<li>Integrated information system is possible</li>
</ul>

<p><br>  </p>

<h3 id="questionstoconsider">Questions to Consider</h3>

<ul>
<li>Will customers pay for convenience so books can be sold for more than the dealer’s asking price?</li>
<li>Will dealers will pay 20% and remain loyal?</li>
<li>Will dealers will list all of their books?</li>
<li>Can Alibris provide better quality control without impacting delivery time?</li>
<li>Can Alibris increase sales?</li>
<li>Will new entrants take their customers?</li>
<li>Will dealers list with their competitors?</li>
</ul>

<p><br>  </p>

<h3 id="revenuemodels">Revenue Models</h3>

<iframe width="100%" height="400" src="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1mWa9ej7v4X4ko9aqGMdm7j5Q4RsO1LBlWu1gN0CrLuk/pubhtml?widget=true&amp;headers=false"></iframe>

<p><br>  </p>

<h3 id="report">Report</h3>

<h4 id="recommendation">Recommendation</h4>

<p>I recommend that Alibris pursue the New Revenue Model.</p>

<p><br>  </p>

<h4 id="newrevenuemodel">New Revenue Model</h4>

<h5 id="netincome">Net Income:</h5>

<table style="width:66%">  
  <tr>
    <th>1999</th>
    <th>2000</th> 
    <th>2001</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>&nbsp;&nbsp;$1,233,000.00</td>
    <td>&nbsp;&nbsp;$2,169,000.00</td>
    <td>&nbsp;&nbsp;$3,105,000.00</td>
  </tr>
</table>

<p><br>  </p>

<h5 id="assumptionshypotheses">Assumptions/Hypotheses:</h5>

<ul>
<li>That the $1,872,500 needed to implement this model can be acquired
<ul><li>It's 1998. Pets.com</li>
<li>Revenue model indicates an ROI of less than 1.5 years</li>
<li>In Santa Clara; In Silicon Valley</li></ul></li>
<li>Customer satisfaction will increase
<ul><li>Increased accountability</li>
<li>Centralized distribution/order consolidation</li>
<li>one box</li>
<li>one invoice</li></ul></li>
</ul>

<p><br>  </p>

<h4 id="oldrevenuemodel">Old Revenue Model</h4>

<h5 id="netincome">Net Income:</h5>

<table style="width:66%">  
  <tr>
    <th>1999</th>
    <th>2000</th> 
    <th>2001</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>&nbsp;&nbsp;$139,999.97</td>
    <td>&nbsp;&nbsp;$235,999.96</td>
    <td>&nbsp;&nbsp;$331,999.95</td>
  </tr>
</table>

<p><br>  </p>

<h5 id="assumptionshypotheses">Assumptions/Hypotheses:</h5>

<ul>
<li>Customer dissatisfaction will eventually drive business away
<ul><li>Customer experience is not easily monitored</li>
<li>Decentralized, no single point of contact for customers</li>
<li>Current 50-60% fulfillment rate, orders shipped within 2 days</li></ul></li>
<li>Competitors will provide better services
<ul><li>If it takes $1,872,500 to make the New Revenue Model happen, someone else can make that happen</li></ul></li>
</ul>

<p><br>  </p>

<h4 id="recommendedactions">Recommended Actions</h4>

<ul>
<li>Obtain funding from outside sources/Venture Capital to fund New Revenue Model </li>
<li>Asses current employee competency.
<ul><li>Restructuring base off of findings</li></ul></li>
</ul>

<p><br></p>

<hr>

<p><br>  </p>

<h2 id="exercise2">Exercise 2</h2>

<h3 id="assumptions">Assumptions</h3>

<ul>
<li>The new revenue model is better than the old revenue model</li>
<li>Thunderstone and Oracle are the only options</li>
</ul>

<p><br>  </p>

<h3 id="questionstoconsider">Questions to Consider</h3>

<ul>
<li>Will what worked for eBay work for Alibris?</li>
<li>Can Oracle succeed?</li>
<li>Will Thunderstone’s software scale?</li>
<li>Can Thunderstone solve the locking problem?</li>
<li>Is Thunderstone’s software maintainable?</li>
<li>Will Thunderstone stay in business?</li>
</ul>

<p><br>  </p>

<h3 id="report">Report</h3>

<h4 id="recommendation">Recommendation</h4>

<p>I recommend that Alibris pursues the Thunderstone Software solution.</p>

<p><br>  </p>

<h4 id="criteria">Criteria</h4>

<h5 id="finances">Finances</h5>

<ul>
<li>Resource utilization, trying to make Oracle work, 3 hires
<ul><li>Level 1 2,500/month</li>
<li>Consultant Level 2 22,000/month</li>
<li>Level 2 4,500/month</li>
<li>Avoid sunk cost fallacy</li></ul></li>
</ul>

<p><br>  </p>

<h5 id="deadlines">Deadlines</h5>

<ul>
<li>Oracle missing deadlines, no identified timeline</li>
<li>Thunderstone waffled whether possible, additional 60-90 days 
<ul><li>Possible credibility for being honest about feasibility, when first asked </li></ul></li>
</ul>

<p><br>  </p>

<h5 id="fulfillment">Fulfillment</h5>

<ul>
<li>Oracle has no known fulfillment date
<ul><li>Large amount of custom coding required to get to work, not plug and play or up-gradable </li></ul></li>
<li>Thunderstone "rescued eBay" from a similar situation 
<ul><li>Thunderstone has a "workaround" to record locking</li>
<li>The infrastructure and hardware for the solution is compatible</li></ul></li>
</ul>

<p><br>  </p>

<h5 id="language">Language</h5>

<ul>
<li>Oracle is ubiquitous</li>
<li>Thunderstone require proprietary Vortex
<ul><li>Hard to find developers</li>
<li>Long term support (LTS) is a concern</li></ul></li>
</ul>

<p><br>  </p>

<h4 id="assumptions">Assumptions</h4>

<h5 id="assumption">Assumption</h5>

<p>Thunderstone will be able to solve the locking problem.  </p>

<h5 id="justification">Justification</h5>

<p>Claims they have a workaround that they already used for eBay.</p>

<p><br>  </p>

<h5 id="assumption">Assumption</h5>

<p>Alibris won't have to worry, in the near term, about having more traffic than eBay.  </p>

<h5 id="justification">Justification</h5>

<p>CEO's own remarks. </p>

<p><br>  </p>

<h5 id="assumption">Assumption</h5>

<p>Thunderstone will be able to speed up queries, search results, and page load times.  </p>

<h5 id="justification">Justification</h5>

<p>Alibris and eBay have similar business functions.</p>

<p><br>  </p>

<h4 id="actions">Actions</h4>

<ul>
<li>Check to see if ebay systems are compatible or similar enough to the Alibris hardware.</li>
<li>Cut ties with Oracle.</li>
<li>Recoup funds from Oracle, due to not putting the software into production.</li>
<li>Reallocate resources to Thunderstone.</li>
<li>Evaluate the human capital required for the Thunderstone implementation, namely the three employees hired for the Oracle roll out.</li>
<li>Clarify whether if Texis is migrating from Vortex to a standard language. Based on result, may need to train in Vortex, start during during 60-90 day implementation.</li>
</ul>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Applied Project]]></title><description><![CDATA[Emerging Technology | IT Consulting | IT Management | Information Technology Consulting | Information Technology Management | Pompeii Consulting]]></description><link>http://localhost:2368/applied-project/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">8e58c10b-29dd-4943-9c9a-d1d54950d478</guid><category><![CDATA[information technology]]></category><category><![CDATA[applied project]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Pompeii Consulting]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2016 17:31:02 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This section will be an applied project on emerging information technology issues. All of the concepts, theories, and frameworks learned in earlier sections will be used to develop an information technology backed transformation plan for a business. Effective presentation of this information will also be discussed and demonstrated.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Information Enabled Business Modeling]]></title><description><![CDATA[Big Data | Data Science | IT Consulting | IT Management | Information Technology Consulting | Information Technology Management | Pompeii Consulting]]></description><link>http://localhost:2368/information-enabled-business-modeling/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">b449c9cb-f109-40a2-9dba-5a7363c02ed6</guid><category><![CDATA[big data]]></category><category><![CDATA[analytical culture]]></category><category><![CDATA[data science]]></category><category><![CDATA[business strategy]]></category><category><![CDATA[business intelligence]]></category><category><![CDATA[data warehouse]]></category><category><![CDATA[databases]]></category><category><![CDATA[business modeling]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Pompeii Consulting]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2016 17:27:50 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In this section we will look at how different organizations and industries are discovering the value of big data. Further, we will inspect the challenges and short comings of certain approaches and applications. The importance an organizational, analytical culture in conjunction with effective data science to create an informed business strategy is paramount.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[IT Services and Project Management]]></title><description><![CDATA[IT Services | Project Management | IT Consulting | IT Management | Information Technology Consulting | Pompeii Consulting]]></description><link>http://localhost:2368/it-services-and-project-management/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">2e8b410f-4434-4772-a959-8b7d12cc4469</guid><category><![CDATA[information technology services]]></category><category><![CDATA[project management]]></category><category><![CDATA[commoditization of hardware]]></category><category><![CDATA[commoditization of software]]></category><category><![CDATA[business process]]></category><category><![CDATA[product development process]]></category><category><![CDATA[service delivery process]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Pompeii Consulting]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2016 17:18:59 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Information technology services, the commoditization of hardware, the commoditization of software, and the business processes involved will be the main focuses of this section. Time will be spent on the information technology product development processes and on the information technology service delivery processes, with special consideration given to being on-time, on-budget, and meeting end user needs, all while using sound management principles.</p>]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>