<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Pompeii Consulting</title><description>IT Consulting | IT Management</description><link>http://localhost:2368/</link><generator>Ghost 0.8</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2016 00:05:16 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:2368/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title>Otis Elevator Case Study</title><description>Customer Relationship Management | IT Consulting | IT Management | Information Technology Consulting | Pompeii Consulting</description><link>http://localhost:2368/otis-information-technology-crm/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">708a9f0b-cac7-462d-91cb-bcbf4b58e806</guid><category>information technolog</category><category>supply chain management</category><category>customer relationship management</category><dc:creator>Pompeii Consulting</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2016 00:05:09 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Focuses on a major transformation of Otis Elevator's infrastructure. Led by the CEO, this transformation represents a remarkable long-term reengineering of all the processes of the firm to drive its operating costs down and service image up. The transformation is the continuation of a process that has been going on for more than 20 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://hbr.org/product/otis-elevator-accelerating-business-transformation-with-it/305048-PDF-ENG" target="_blank"&gt;Harvard Business Review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The IT tools being used by Otis in 2004 were simple – database, workflow software, Intranets and Extranets, email – but the benefits appeared to be extraordinary. What are the things that really had changed in the company over the last few years leading up to 2005?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Otis Elevator’s earliest initiatives had been to build the business through massive acquisitions. Through these acquisitions, Otis was able to expand its customer base extensively and became the “largest manufacturer, installer, and servicer of elevators, escalators, and moving walkways in the world.”    While these acquisitions had been extremely profitable, Otis leadership knew that without consolidation and standardization of products and services within the company, that continued profitability would not be sustainable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the years leading up to 2005, Otis leadership recognized their business strategy needed to shift to compare to benchmark companies like UPS who had institutionalized customer service, and developed standardized  workflow processes and metrics to govern every customer interaction and internal activity. The vision moving forward was to become the recognized leader in service excellence among all companies – not just elevator companies – worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to align the  new vision with its business strategy, Otis needed to reduce the number of modules in use and lower project costs.  The SIMBA program was introduced to “fundamentally change the architecture and ultimately the design process; the goal was a standard-interface, modular-based architecture defining modules and subsystems from which all Otis elevator systems could be created.”  Also introduced with the SIMBA program was standard terminology. In the past, Otis verbiage varied so much throughout the organization that communications within the company could be misconstrued or misinterpreted. Through the implementation of a standardized terminology, important concepts such as “contracts, proposals, projects and field modules” would have the same meaning to any party requiring information as to the status of one of these steps in the development or implementation phase. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tony Black of Otis Field Operations shared the “e-Logistics program which is based on the maturity of SIP.  If we hadn’t done SIP, and just did the e-Logistics program, it would have taken much longer.”   In sum,  Otis Elevator was no longer an “old-line can’t miss industrial firm, which only needed caretakers” as was the description provided by Tom Wolfe decades earlier. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the e-Logistics program, best practice from SIP are baked into the company and institutionalized to achieve that continuous transformation. How do the systems that comprise the e-Logistics program bake in an institutionalized best practice?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Implementation of the  e-Logistics information transformation project provided Otis’ IT systems with the resources needed to “facilitate business process re-engineering that was taking place throughout.” This was  accomplished by taking the lessons learned from the initial Sales and Installation Process (SIP), and integrating them into a company-wide IT solution geared toward its evolving business model. The  e-Logistics program was built over a two year timeframe by gathering information from subject matter experts in the fields of “sales, field, and order management along with IT project managers.” By doing this, Otis was able to demonstrate the ideals of Pearlson and Saunders when they wrote, “In an organization that operates successfully, an overriding business strategy drives both organizational strategy and information strategy.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From an organizational perspective, the Project Proposal phase used a mandatory electronic pre-bid checklist which had to be approved by both the sales representative and the field-installation supervisor. Prior to e-Logistics, this was a manual process, and often times the field-installation supervisor did not even see the checklist or know the requirements until it was time for install.  Instituting this pre-bid checklist ensured the sales and field organizations worked together from the beginning of the process, increased process cohesion and allowed for minimal delays at install.  From an IS perspective, former manual systems, such as booking, validation and scheduling, became centrally automated.  This allowed for the e-Logistics software to automatically push data to appropriate supervisory and financial personnel.  Automated information sharing ensures each  party receives information  efficiently and decreases the need for middle  management. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Order Fulfillment phase is another example of institutionalization, as field-installation supervisors were responsible for relaying when job sites were ready for deliveries.  The automated email service within e-Logistics prompts supervisors to check in on sites,  allows for status updates and face-to-face interactions with contractors.  This demonstrates how e-Logistics institutionalized site preparation, allowing for the implementation of the “pull” system.  Otis’ Tony Black said that the automated email and reminder process, “forces critical steps of SIP and makes good process part of the way you do business.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By taking best practices from SIP and integrating them into the automated, e-Logistics program, it ensured both present and future Otis employees would execute these best practices.  This institutionalized, “baked in” program prevents best practices from being lost in two ways: 1) Mandatory use for nearly all employees, which helped Otis move away from many inefficient  manual processes and 2) best practices were now being held within the program, preventing an individual leaving the company and taking job-specific or institutional knowledge with them.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://pompeiiconsulting.com/strategic-value-of-information-technology"&gt;Strategic Value of Information Technology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Productivity Analysis</title><description>Productivity Analysis | Productivity Growth | Efficiency Change | Technical Change | IT Consulting | IT Management | Pompeii Consulting
</description><link>http://localhost:2368/business-information-technology-productivity-analysis/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">755bbe7e-5fbc-4616-b710-dc18c2e3e89d</guid><category>information technology</category><category>productivity analysis</category><category>productivity</category><category>efficiency</category><category>productivity growth</category><category>efficiency change</category><category>technical change</category><dc:creator>Pompeii Consulting</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2016 00:35:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h3 id="performanceevaluation"&gt;Performance Evaluation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;"You can't manage what you can't measure." 
- Peter Ducker
&lt;br&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="productivity"&gt;Productivity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;productivity = output produced / input consumed&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;always a rational number, 0 &amp;lt;= p &amp;lt; ∞&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id="productivitygrowth"&gt;Productivity Growth&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;productivity growth = productivity at t+1 / productivity at t&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;always an index, 0 &amp;lt;= pg &amp;lt;= 1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id="efficiency"&gt;Efficiency&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;efficiency = output produced / output maximum &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;aways a ratio or percentage, 0 &amp;lt;= e &amp;lt; 1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id="efficiencychange"&gt;Efficiency Change&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;efficiency change = efficiency at t+1 / efficiency at t&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;always an index, 0 &amp;lt;= ec &amp;lt;= 1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id="technicalchange"&gt;Technical Change&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Production frontier is the line that specifies the ideal maximum output produced at any input level&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;technical change = slope of production frontier at t+1 / slope of production frontier at t&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;always an index,  0 &amp;lt;= pf &amp;lt;= 1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id="productivitygrowthefficiencychangetechnicalchange"&gt;Productivity Growth = Efficiency Change * Technical Change&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="productivityanalysis"&gt;Productivity Analysis&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information technology and business management need to know how effectively and efficiently activities are being performed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;effectiveness: do the right thing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;efficiency: the the thing right&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the ability to measure and compare information technology activities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;gauge how well information technology is performing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;see if information technology is meeting the demands of the firm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;challenge is choosing what and when to measure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;monitor and control information technology activities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improve performance and demonstrate information technology value&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://pompeiiconsulting.com/strategic-value-of-information-technology"&gt;Strategic Value of Information Technology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>IT and Business Organization Strategy</title><description>Telecommuting | Virtual Teams | Organizational Structures | IT Consulting | IT Management | Pompeii Consulting</description><link>http://localhost:2368/information-technology-business-organization-strategy/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6f889599-1c69-4f14-be00-8ddca9651424</guid><category>organizational strategy</category><category>data mining</category><category>electronic collaboration</category><category>organizational structures</category><category>networked organization</category><category>telecommuting</category><category>data collection</category><category>virtual teams</category><dc:creator>Pompeii Consulting</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2016 23:40:57 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h3 id="organizationalstrategy"&gt;Organizational Strategy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Organization's design and work processes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optimize organizational design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optimize management control systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Organization structure is the way of designing an organization so decision rights are correctly allocated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The structure of reporting relationships reflects the flow of communication and decision making in an organization.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="organizationalstructures"&gt;Organizational Structures&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id="hierarchicalorganizationalstructure"&gt;Hierarchical Organizational Structure&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Description: Bureaucratic with defined levels of management&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Characteristics: Division of labor specialization, unity of command&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Best Environment: Stable Certain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basis of Structure: Primary function&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Power Structure: Centralized&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Key Supporting Technology: Mainframe, centralized data and processing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id="flatorganizationalstructure"&gt;Flat Organizational Structure&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Description: Decision-making pushed down to lowest level&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Characteristics: Informal roles, planning and control; often small, young organizations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Best Environment: Unstable Uncertain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basis of Structure: Primary function&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Power Structure: Centralized&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Key Supporting Technology: Personal computers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id="matrixorganizationalstructure"&gt;Matrix Organizational Structure&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Description: Workers assigned to two or more supervisors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Characteristics: Dual reporting based on function/purpose&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Best Environment: Unstable Uncertain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basis of Structure: Functions and purpose&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Power Structure: Distributed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Key Supporting Technology: Networks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id="networkedorganizationalstructure"&gt;Networked Organizational Structure&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Description: Formal/informal communication networks that connect all&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Characteristics: Known for flexibility and adaptability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Best Environment: Unstable Uncertain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basis of Structure: Networks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Power Structure: Distributed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Key Supporting Technology: Intranets and Internet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Employees share their knowledge and experience,and participate in making key organizational decisions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information Systems are fundamental to process design, improve process efficiency, effectiveness, and flexibility.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="informalnetworks"&gt;Informal Networks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id="informalrelationshipsdesignatedbymanagement"&gt;Informal Relationships designated by management&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;working on a project&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;job rotation program&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;call upon past co-workers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id="unintendednetworks"&gt;Unintended Networks&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;work proximity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;shared interests&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;family ties&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;politics crossing organizations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id="socialnetworking"&gt;Social Networking&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;links individuals together&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;find experts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;meet colleges&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;find relevant experience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;crosses traditional organizations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="managementcontrol"&gt;Management Control&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information technology affects how managers control their organizations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Management control systems respond to goals established through planning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Goals are periodically adjusted&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Control work at process level&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Organizational structure will dictate level of managerial control&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information Systems in Management Control Processes:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;data collection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;evaluation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;communication&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gives management more time to make decisions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="datacollectionandinformationtechnology"&gt;Data Collection and Information Technology&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monitoring work using information technology&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;keystrokes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;time spent on a task&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;who is contacted &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id="organizationaldesignchallengesindatacollection"&gt;Organizational design challenges in data collection&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;embedded monitoring tasks within everyday work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reduce the negative impacts to monitored workers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id="datacollectionsoftware"&gt;Data collection software&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;can backfire, cause stress&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;used to reward, not just punish&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="evaluationandinformationtechnology"&gt;Evaluation and Information Technology&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information Technology enables evaluating against standard data and historical data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;models can be built&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;simulations designed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;managers can easily understand work progress and performance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;analysis paralysis: too much data or information&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how feedback is communicated effects behavior&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;information handled discreetly and appropriately&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="incentivesandrewardandinformationtechnology"&gt;Incentives and Reward and Information Technology&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ways to incentivize good performance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;can make employees feel good and boost morale&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;use websites to recognize high performers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reward with new technology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information Technology allows for complex reward systems, shared and team based&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;consider metrics and qualitative data in assigning compensation and rewards&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="informationsystemsandculture"&gt;Information Systems and Culture&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;culture is one managerial lever &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;set of values and beliefs about what is desirable and undesirable in a community of people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;culture is always changing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;national culture differences effect information systems development and use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;understand and appreciate cultural values, practices, and subtleties&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improve communications and reduce conflict&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;listening, framing, and responding to feedback&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="informationtechnologyandvirtualorganization"&gt;Information Technology and Virtual Organization&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;time and place of work blended&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;can do work at home, own own time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;virtual organization is a networked structure that makes it possible for individuals to work and live anywhere&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;internet and corporate intranets create the opportunity for individuals to work from anywhere&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;virtual organizations depend upon collaboration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="workdesignframework"&gt;Work Design Framework&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Used to asses how emerging information technology affects work&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What work will be performed?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who is going to do the work?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where will the work be performed?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When will the work be performed?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can information technology increase the effectiveness of the workers doing the work?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="informationtechnologytofacilitatecommunication"&gt;Information Technology to Facilitate Communication&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;email&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;intranet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;instant messaging (IM)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Voice over IP (VoIP)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Video Teleconferencing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unified Communications (UC)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Really Simple Syndication (RSS)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Virtual Private Network (VPN)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;File Transfer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="informationtechnologytofacilitatecollaboration"&gt;Information Technology to Facilitate Collaboration&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;social networking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;virtual worlds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;web logs (blogs)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;wikis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;groupware&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="informationtechnologychangesnatureofwork"&gt;Information Technology Changes Nature of Work&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;creates many new jobs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;redefines existing ones
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;the way work is done&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;communication patterns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;organizational decision making&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;information processing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;collaboration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ways to connect&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how to manage workforce
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;supervising&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;evaluating&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;rewarding&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;hiring&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;careers
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;programers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;business analysts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;information technology managers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;hardware assemblers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;web site designers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;softwares sales personnel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;information technology consultants&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id="traditionalsubjectiveobservation"&gt;Traditional: Subjective Observation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Supervision: Personal and informal. Manager is usually present or relies on others to ensure that employee is present and productive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evaluation: Focus is on process through direct observation. Manager sees how employee performed at work. Subjective (personal) factors are very important.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compensation: Often individually-based.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hiring: Personal with little reliance on computers. Often more reliance on clerical skills.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id="modernobjectiveobservation"&gt;Modern: Objective Observation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Supervision: Electronic or assessed by deliverable. As long as the employee is producing value, he does not need formal supervisions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evaluation: Focus is on output by deliverable (e.g., produce a report by a certain date) or by target (e.g., meet a sales quota). As long as deliverables are produced and/or targets are achieved, the employee is meeting performance expectations adequately. Subjective factors may be less important and harder to gauge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compensation: Often team-based or contractually spelled out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hiring: Often electronic with recruiting websites and electronic testing. More information- based work that requires a higher level of IT skills.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="telecommuting"&gt;Telecommuting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Started in 1970's&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gained popularity in late 1990's&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reduces stress&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;geographic flexibility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;higher productivity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tapping housebound individuals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;difficult for managers to evaluate performance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;workers must be extremely self disciplined&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;may end up working more hours&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;can be disconnected from corporate culture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;offshoring enabled by same technology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id="managerialissuesintelecommuting"&gt;Managerial Issues in Telecommuting&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;planning, business, and support tasks must be redesigned to support mobile and remote workers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;training should be offered so all workers understand the new work environment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;employees must be self starters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;managers must fined new ways to evaluate and supervise employees without seeing them everyday&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id="virtualteams"&gt;Virtual Teams&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geographically or organizationally dispersed coworkers assembled using information technology and telecommunications&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;same drivers as telecommuting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;teams in different parts of the world can cooperate
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;get jobs done faster&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;around the clock&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;different time zones&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;security is harder to ensure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lose nuances of face to face conversation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;trust may be slower to form&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;diversity of team members
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;language&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;culture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;customs&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id="lifecycleofvirtualteams"&gt;Life Cycle of Virtual Teams&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h5 id="preparation"&gt;Preparation&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;mission statement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;personnel selection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;task design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;rewards sustem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;technology selection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;technology installment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id="launch"&gt;Launch&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;kickoff meetings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;getting acquainted&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;goal clarification&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;norm development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id="performancemanagement"&gt;Performance Management&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;leadership&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;communication&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;conflict resolution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;task accomplishment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;motivation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;knowledge management&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;norm enforcement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;norm shaping&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id="teamdevelopment"&gt;Team Development&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;assessment of needs and deficits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;individual or team training&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;evaluation of training effects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;trust building&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id="disbanding"&gt;Disbanding&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;recognition of achievements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reintegration of team members&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id="managerialissuesinvirtualteams"&gt;Managerial Issues in Virtual Teams&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;require different style and type of management&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;observation is less likely to occur&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;performance is more likely to be based on output&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;providing feedback is important&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;compensation should be based on team performance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;align rewards with achievement of team goals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;challenges
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;communication&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;technology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;diversity&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="informationtechnologyinducedchange"&gt;Information Technology Induced Change&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in order to avoid resistance to change, must actively manage the change process&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;employee attitudes may change if perception of new system is it helps them do more work, better work for the same or less effort, and it is easy to use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;employee participation in system design and implementation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="technologyacceptancemodel"&gt;Technology Acceptance Model&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Individual Differences&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;System Characteristics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Social Influence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facilitating Conditions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology Acceptance Model (TAM)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perceived Usefulness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perceived Ease of Use
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Behavioral Intention&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use Behavior&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://pompeiiconsulting.com/strategic-value-of-information-technology"&gt;Strategic Value of Information Technology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Strategy and the Internet</title><description>Internet Business |Competitive Advantage IT Consulting | IT Management | Information Technology Consulting | Pompeii Consulting</description><link>http://localhost:2368/competitive-advantage-internet/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">8fd2b1bf-5275-45ae-9ede-462e05540e77</guid><category>business strategy</category><category>information technology</category><category>information management</category><category>competitive advantage</category><category>internet</category><category>disruptive innovation</category><category>information strategy</category><category>organizational strategy</category><dc:creator>Pompeii Consulting</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2016 18:34:20 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Many of the pioneers of Internet business, both dot-coms and established companies, have competed in ways that violate nearly every precept of good strategy. Rather than focus on profits, they have chased customers indiscriminately through discounting, channel incentives, and advertising. Rather than concentrate on delivering value that earns an attractive price from customers, they have pursued indirect revenues such as advertising and click-through fees. Rather than make trade-offs, they have rushed to offer every conceivable product or service. It did not have to be this way--and it does not have to be in the future. When it comes to reinforcing a distinctive strategy, Michael Porter argues, the Internet provides a better technological platform than previous generations of IT. Gaining competitive advantage does not require a radically new approach to business; it requires building on the proven principles of effective strategy. Porter argues that, contrary to recent thought, the Internet is not disruptive to most existing industries and established companies. It rarely nullifies important sources of competitive advantage in an industry; it often makes them even more valuable. And as all companies embrace Internet technology, the Internet itself will be neutralized as a source of advantage. Robust competitive advantages will arise instead from traditional strengths such as unique products, proprietary content, and distinctive physical activities. Internet technology may be able to fortify those advantages, but it is unlikely to supplant them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://hbr.org/product/strategy-and-the-internet/R0103D-PDF-ENG" target="_blank"&gt;Harvard Business Review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why isn’t a business strategy sufficient for a company to determine how it can leverage IT for competitive advantage? Based on the descriptions of "Strategy and the Internet", how would you characterize Walgreens’ business strategy and IS strategy in using the Internet for its business?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Business strategy alone is not sufficient for a company to determine how it can leverage IT for competitive advantage. As stated in the IS Strategy Triangle slide, “companies are said to be in alignment when their business strategy is supported/enabled/driven by their information strategy.” The business strategy must be adhered to first and foremost with the organizational and information strategy supporting and aligning with it. In order to achieve a sustainable competitive advantage, the business needs “to be more profitable than the average performer,” according to the Strategy and the Internet article. The article further indicates that operational effectiveness, and strategic positioning are key drivers for competitive advantage. Business strategy and IT both come with their own strengths.  In Managing and Using Information Systems, the author states that “IS and business maturity must be aligned to provide the right level of information resources to the business.” It is imperative that IT be leveraged as a participant in the overall business strategy, but sustainability and profitability need to be the key drivers. &lt;br&gt;
Walgreens’ business and IS strategy can be characterized as a two-pronged model for success. By integrating the internet (i.e. online ordering services), rather than cannibalizing or forfeiting their established core business strategy (brick and mortar stores), the company was able to increase the success of its existing business model through the use of a complementary arrangement between the two channels. Walgreens embraced the ideals from the article that stated, “Established companies will be most successful when they deploy Internet technology to reconfigure traditional activities or when they find new combinations of Internet and traditional approaches.” This ideal allowed them to reach a larger, more diverse customer base, while continuing to satisfy its existing one. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;
Use the Porter’s 5 competitive forces model, perform an analysis similar to the one by Porter on pages 5-7 in “Strategy and the Internet,” and predict how the phenomena of Web 2.0 like social networking would influence industry structure and profitability for an average firm?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="threatofnewentrants"&gt;Threat of New Entrants&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(-) “Sharing economy” has drastically reduced the barriers to entry for service work, both on-site and remote. (-) Lower barrier to entry for products, ideas can be shared and go viral over social media. (-) Crowdfunding, such as Kickstarter reduce capital requirements for entrants into a product category. (+) Synergy between established physical locations and mobile, such as grubhub and postmates, adds value to existing infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="bargainingpowerofbuyers"&gt;Bargaining Power of Buyers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(-) Bargaining power of end user increases due to ease and availability of information about new, alternative, and rival products. (-) Buyers can insinuate a bidding war, by having firms compete on price (-) Buyers have drastically increased power and voice due to social media, with a tweet can become a national headline. (+) Happy and vocal customers with clout on social media can advocate for a firm, for free or through sponsorship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="bargainingpowerofsuppliers"&gt;Bargaining Power of Suppliers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(+) Sites and platforms such as Alibaba and SalesForce allow for more choice and alternatives when a firm is selecting a supplier for a product or service that can increase fit and thus efficiency. (+) “Sharing Economy” has allowed for an alternative to some services, à la carte and in a reliable fashion; less overhead, more flexibility. (-) Suppliers, of both goods and services, can more easily go direct to market, bypassing the firm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="threatofsubstitutes"&gt;Threat of Substitutes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(-) Social/viral advertising allows for alternative products to gain consumer mind share more easily than before. (-) Mobile allows for substitute products to be found not just at home but from nearly anywhere, even in a firm’s retail location. (-) “Sharing economy” has allowed easy competition on the services side, creating alternatives that never existed before. (+) Social engagement and brand recognition can help buffer against new entrants, by forming a relationship with customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="industrycompetitors"&gt;Industry Competitors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(-) Social engagement with customers is mandatory order to stay relevant and competitive to others in the industry. (-) Reduced competitive advantages in organizational systems as SaaS’s such as SalesForce continue to dominate the market. (+) Increased similarities in organizational systems can increase the ease of acquisitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://pompeiiconsulting.com/strategic-value-of-information-technology"&gt;Strategic Value of Information Technology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Business Basics</title><description>Economics | IT Consulting | IT Management | Information Technology Consulting | Information Technology Management | Pompeii Consulting</description><link>http://localhost:2368/business-information-technology/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6cd6b498-0442-4aac-8bf0-d821ab5f821e</guid><category>business</category><category>profit</category><category>law of demand</category><category>law of supply</category><category>network effect</category><category>economics</category><dc:creator>Pompeii Consulting</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2016 22:17:09 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is not from the benevolence of the butcher, the brewer, or the baker, that we expect our dinner, but from their regard to their own interest&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adam Smith, &lt;em&gt;The Wealth of Nations&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses try to maximize profit &lt;br&gt;
Profit, net income, net earnings, bottom line (of income statement)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Profit = Total Revenues - Total Costs &lt;br&gt;
Profit = (Price x Quantity) - (Total Fixed Costs + Total Variable Costs)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To increase profit&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;increase total revenue
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;increase price&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;increase quantity&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;decrease total costs
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;decrease fixed costs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;decrease variable costs&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="lawofdemand"&gt;Law of Demand&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inverse relationship between price and quantity&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="demandsideeconomiesofscale"&gt;Demand Side Economies of Scale&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Violates the Law of Demand&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Luxury Goods: as price increases so does quantity
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Rolex, Gucci&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Network Goods: as quantity increases so does price
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Microsoft Office, Skype, Facebook&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="supplysideeconomics"&gt;Supply Side Economics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Desire to decrease average fixed cost and average variable cost&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="supplysideeconomiesofscale"&gt;Supply Side Economies of Scale&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Increase quantity leads to a decrease in average costs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Average Fixed Costs = Total Fixed Costs / Quantity
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Fixed cost leverage&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Average Variable Costs = Total Variable Costs / Quantity
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;volume discount, learning effect, division of labor&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="maximizeprofit"&gt;Maximize Profit&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marginal Revenues = Marginal Costs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="informationtechnology"&gt;Information Technology&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id="impactsonprofitability"&gt;Impacts on Profitability&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Network Effects
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Winner take all systems&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Software
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;large fixed cost&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;near zero variable costs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;example: freeware&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information Technology enhanced learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information Technology based transformation of industry structure
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;example: Netflix vs Blockbuster&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="businessethics"&gt;Business Ethics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Resources be used efficiently and allocated effectively&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Greatest economic value can be created&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://pompeiiconsulting.com/strategic-value-of-information-technology"&gt;Strategic Value of Information Technology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Strategic Alignment</title><description>IT Strategy | Competitive Advantage | IT Consulting | IT Management | Information Technology Consulting | Pompeii Consulting</description><link>http://localhost:2368/strategic-alignment/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">dd62b66a-77c1-40e7-91b2-ad8d6080feb7</guid><category>Harvard Business Review</category><category>information systems</category><category>competitive advantage</category><category>information technology</category><category>business strategy</category><category>strategic advantage</category><category>value chain</category><category>Value of IT</category><dc:creator>Pompeii Consulting</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2016 22:25:16 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Many have argued that the Internet renders strategy obsolete. In reality, the opposite is true. Because the Internet tends to weaken industry profitability without providing proprietary operational advantages, it is more important than ever for companies to distinguish themselves through strategy. The winners will be those that view the Internet as a complement to, not a cannibal of, traditional ways of competing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://hbr.org/product/strategy-and-the-internet/R0103D-PDF-ENG" target="_blank"&gt;Harvard Business Review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="informationsystemsstrategytriangle"&gt;Information Systems Strategy Triangle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Business Strategy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Organization Strategy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Information Strategy&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Successful when in alignment&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Overriding business strategy, drive organizational and information strategies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change in 1 require change in the other 2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id="strategy"&gt;Strategy&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;coordinated set of actions to fulfill goals, objectives, and purposes; it involves mission and vision.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="businessstrategy"&gt;Business Strategy&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;plan articulating where a business seeks to go and how it expects to get there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="sustainablecompetitiveadvantage"&gt;Sustainable competitive advantage:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cost leadership: lower cost&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;differentiation: unique product&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;focus: limited scope&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id="hypercompetitionmodelsuggestthatthespeedandmarketdynamicscreateanenvironmentsuchthat"&gt;Hyper-competition model suggest that the speed and market dynamics create an environment such that:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;every advantage is quickly eroded&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sustaining an advantage can be a deadly distraction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;goal of advantage should be disruption, not sustainability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;initiatives are achieved through series of small steps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GE Destroy Your Business Project&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="strategicadvantagesrelatedtoinformationsystems"&gt;Strategic Advantages Related to Information Systems&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Managers cannot rely solely on IT to make IT decisions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Business strategy drives Information Systems decisions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change in Information Systems potential triggers business reassessment
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Internet, mobile, social networks&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Framework &lt;br&gt;
Porter's Generic Strategies &lt;br&gt;
Key Idea &lt;br&gt;
Competitive advantage: cost, differentiate, focus &lt;br&gt;
App to Information Systems &lt;br&gt;
Information Systems chosen to match strategy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Famework &lt;br&gt;
Dynamic Environment Strategies &lt;br&gt;
Key Idea &lt;br&gt;
Speed, agility, and aggressive moves and counter moves create competitive advantage &lt;br&gt;
App to Information Systems &lt;br&gt;
Information Systems critical to achieving the required speed of innovation, moves, and counter moves. In a constant state of flux/development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="organizationstrategyframework"&gt;Organization Strategy Framework&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;organization design and choices to make it work processes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How a company organizes to achieve it goals and implement its business strategy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Business Diamond identifies core components of the org's plan.
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;tasks and structure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;management and measurement systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;values and belief&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;business processes&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="managerialleversframework"&gt;Managerial Levers Framework&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strategy, Execution, Organizational Effectiveness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Success = organization variables + control variables + culture variables&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Organization variables
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;business processes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;formal Reporting relationships&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;informal networks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;decision rights&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Control variables
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;decision rights&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;planning &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;performance measurements and evaluation&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Culture variables
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Values&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Incentives and rewards&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id="informationsystemsstrategy"&gt;Information Systems Strategy&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the plan an organization uses to provide information services; helps implement business strategy and determine the company's capabilities&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="infrastructurecomponents"&gt;Infrastructure Components:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What | Who | Where &lt;br&gt;
Hardware: system components | individual users and managers | physical location &lt;br&gt;
Software: programs, applications, and utilities | individuals and managers | hardware it is on an that hardwares location &lt;br&gt;
Networking: Diagram of connection between hardware and software | individuals, managers, and company from | nodes, wires, and other media location &lt;br&gt;
Data: Bits of information in system | individuals and managers | information is stored&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="erasofinformationusage"&gt;Eras of Information Usage&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Role of IT | Justification | Target | Models &lt;br&gt;
Technology | Basis | Economics &lt;br&gt;
60's &lt;br&gt;
Efficiency | ROI | Organization | Application &lt;br&gt;
Mainframe | Scarcity | Bundled &lt;br&gt;
70's &lt;br&gt;
Effectiveness | Productivity| Organization &amp;amp; Group | Data &lt;br&gt;
Minicomputers| Scarcity | Bundled &lt;br&gt;
80's &lt;br&gt;
Strategic | Competitive | Individual &amp;amp; Group | User &lt;br&gt;
Microcomputers | Scarcity | Bundled &lt;br&gt;
1990's &lt;br&gt;
Strategic/Transform | Competitive | Business Process | Business &lt;br&gt;
Client-Server | Plentitude | Separated &lt;br&gt;
2000's &lt;br&gt;
Value &amp;amp; Partnership | Adding Value | Customer/Supplier | Knowledge &lt;br&gt;
Internet | Plentitude | Separated &lt;br&gt;
2010's &lt;br&gt;
Community &amp;amp; Social | Relationships | Customer/Employee | People &lt;br&gt;
Social, Mobile , Cloud | Plentitude | Relationships Bundled&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data -&gt; Information -&gt; Knowledge -&gt; Intelligence -&gt; Data&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information Resources: data, technology, people, and processes available to perform business processes and tasks &lt;br&gt;
Move from efficiency model to value creation model&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="informationtechnologyasset"&gt;Information Technology Asset:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thing or idea used in creating, producing, and offering a product&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information Technology Infrastructure: Hardware, software, network, data components, proprietary technology, web-based services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information Repository: Critical information about customers that can be used to gain strategic advantage. Much of this information is increasingly available on the web&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id="informationtechnologycapability"&gt;Information Technology Capability:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learned or developed over time to create, produce, or offer a product&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Technical Skill: Proficiency in systems analysis and design; programming skills&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IT Management Skills: Being knowledgeable about business processes and managing systems to support them; evaluating technology options; envisioning creative Information Systems solutions to business problems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Relationship Skills: having a good relationship between IT and business managers; have a good relationship with an outsourcing vendor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="valueofinformationresources"&gt;Value of Information Resources&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Network Effect: Value of a network node increases to a person or organization when others join the network. Rather than production cost (close to zero), valued is calculated as value to the buyer, which increases along with the size of the network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="thestrategiclandscape"&gt;The Strategic Landscape&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Managers confront elements that influence the competitive environment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slim tolerance for error&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Managers must take multiple views of the strategic landscape
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;External: Porter's 5 Forces model&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Internal:Porter's Value Chain model&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Resource-Based: Identify types of Information Systems resources and capabilities needed&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="portersfiveforcesmodel"&gt;Porter's Five Forces Model:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shape external competitive environment&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Threat of New Entrants
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;switching costs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;access to distribution channels&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;economies of scale&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bargaining Power of Buyers
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;buyer selection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;switching costs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;differentiation&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bargaining Power of Suppliers
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;selection of supplier&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;threat of backward integration&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Threat of Substitutes (equivalent or superior alternative)
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;redefine products and services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improve price/performance&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Industry Competitors
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;cost-effectiveness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;market access&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;differentiation of product/service&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="portersvaluechainmodel"&gt;Porter's Value Chain Model:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Internal activities that crate, deliver, and support products and services&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="primaryactivities"&gt;Primary Activities:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;relates directly to the value created in a product or service&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inbound Logistics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Operations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Outbound Logistics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Marketing and Sales&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Service &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id="supportactivities"&gt;Support Activities:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;make it possible for the primary activities to exist and remain coordinated&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Organization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Human Resources&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Technology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Purchasing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="valuechainsystem"&gt;Value Chain System&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Advantage comes from understanding how information is used within and across the value chains in the system &lt;br&gt;
ex: supply chain management (SCM) &lt;br&gt;
supplier value chain -&gt; firm value chain -&gt; channel value chain -&gt; buyer value chain&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="resourcebasedviewrbv"&gt;Resource-Based View (RBV)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gain competitive advantage through the use of information resources&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attain Competitive Advantage: rare and valuable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sustain Competitive Advantage: difficult to substitute, imitate, and relatively immobile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="potentialrisks"&gt;Potential Risks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Awakening Sleeping Giant: large competitor with more capital incentives to implement Information Systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Demonstrating bad timing: customers not ready for new technology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Poor Information Systems implementation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Failing to deliver firms target, usually fail&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Web-based alternative removes advantages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Running afoul of the law&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="cocreatinginformationtechnologyandbusinessstrategy"&gt;Co-Creating Information Technology and Business Strategy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information core component of product or service offered by firms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information Technology strategy should enable and drive business strategy: co-created&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High Information Technology and Business strategic alignment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id="strategyandtheinternet"&gt;Strategy and the Internet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two factors determine profitability&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;industry structure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sustainable competitive advantage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="howtheinternetinfluenceindustrystructure"&gt;How the Internet Influence Industry Structure&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id="threatofsubstituteproductsorservices"&gt;Threat of substitute products or services&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(+) By making the overall industry more efficient, the Internet can expand the size of the market&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(-) The proliferation of Internet approaches creates new substitution threats&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id="bargainingpowerbargainingpowerofsuppliers"&gt;Bargaining power Bargaining power of Suppliers&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(+/-) Procurement using the Internet tends to raise bargaining power over suppliers, though it can also give suppliers access to more customers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(-) The Internet provides a channel for suppliers to reach end users, reducing the leverage of intervening companies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(-) Internet procurement and digital markets tend to give all companies equal access to suppliers, and gravitate procurement to standardized products that
reduce differentiation  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(-) Reduced barriers to entry and the proliferation of competitors downstream shifts power to suppliers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id="rivalryamongexistingcompetitors"&gt;Rivalry among existing competitors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(-) Reduces differences among competitors as offerings are difficult to keep proprietary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(-) Migrates competition to price&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(-) Widens the geographic market, increasing the number of competitors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(-) Lowers variable cost relative to fixed cost, increasing pressures for price discounting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id="buyers"&gt;Buyers&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h5 id="bargainingpowerofchannels"&gt;Bargaining power of channels&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(+) Eliminates powerful
channels or improves bargaining power over traditional channels&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id="bargainingpowerofendusers"&gt;Bargaining power of end users&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(-) Shifts bargaining power to end consumers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(-) Reduces switching costs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id="barrierstoentry"&gt;Barriers to Entry&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(-) Reduces barriers to entry such as the need for a sales force, access to channels, and physical assets – anything that Internet technology eliminates or makes easier to do reduces barriers to entry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(-) Internet applications are difficult to keep proprietary from new entrants&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(-) A flood of new entrants has come into many industries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="impactsoftheinternetoncompetitiveadvantage"&gt;Impacts of the internet on competitive advantage&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;operational effectiveness -&gt; competitive convergence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;strategic position -&gt; convenience, service, specialization, customization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="sixprinciplesofstrategicpositioning"&gt;Six Principles of Strategic Positioning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;right goal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;value proposition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;distinct value chain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tradeoffs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;continuity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Internet should complement, not canalize traditional actives &lt;br&gt;
Strategic imperatives for dot-coms vs established companies&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="prominentapplicationsoftheinternetinthevaluechain"&gt;Prominent Applications of the Internet in the Value Chain&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id="supportactivities"&gt;Support Activities&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h5 id="firminfrastructure"&gt;Firm Infrastructure&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Web-based, distributed financial and ERP systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On-line investor relations (e.g., information dissemination, broadcast conference calls)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id="humanresourcemanagement"&gt;Human Resource Management&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self-service personnel and benefits administration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Web-based training&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Internet-based sharing and dissemination of company information&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Electronic time and expense reporting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id="technologydevelopment"&gt;Technology Development&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collaborative product design across locations and among multiple value-system participants&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Knowledge directories accessible from all parts of the organization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Real-time access by R&amp;amp;D to on-line sales and service information&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id="procurement"&gt;Procurement&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Internet-enabled demand planning; real-time available-to-promise/capable-to-promise and fulfillment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Other linkage of purchase, inventory, and forecasting systems with suppliers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automated “requisition to pay”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Direct and indirect procurement via marketplaces, exchanges, auctions, and buyer-seller matching&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id="primaryactivities"&gt;Primary Activities&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h5 id="inboundlogistics"&gt;Inbound Logistics&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Real-time integrated scheduling, shipping, warehouse management, demand management and planning, and advanced planning and scheduling across the company and its suppliers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dissemination throughout the company of real-time inbound and in-progress inventory data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id="operations"&gt;Operations&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Integrated information exchange, scheduling, and decision making in in-house plants, contract assemblers, and components suppliers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Real-time available-to- promise and capable- to-promise information available to the sales force and channels&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id="outboundlogistics"&gt;Outbound Logistics&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Real-time transaction of orders whether initiated by an end consumer, a sales person, or a channel partner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automated customer- specific agreements and contract terms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customer and channel ac- cess to product development and delivery status&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collaborative integration with customer forecasting systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Integrated channel management including information exchange, warranty claims, and con- tract management (versioning, process control)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id="marketingandsales"&gt;Marketing and Sales&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On-line sales channels including Web sites and marketplaces&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Real-time inside and outside access to customer information, product catalogs, dynamic pricing, inventory availability, on-line submission of quotes, and order entry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On-line product configurators&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customer-tailored market- ing via customer profiling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Push advertising&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tailored on-line access&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Real-time customer feed-back through Web surveys, opt-in/opt-out marketing, and promotion response tracking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id="aftersalesservice"&gt;After-Sales Service&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On-line support of customer service representatives through e-mail response management, billing integration, co- browse, chat, “call me now,” voice-over-IP, and other uses of video streaming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customer self-service via Web sites and intelligent service request processing including updates to billing and shipping profiles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Real-time field service access to customer account review, schematic review, parts availability and ordering, work-order update, and service parts management&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://pompeiiconsulting.com/strategic-value-of-information-technology" target="_blank"&gt;Strategic Value of Information Technology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Alibris Case Study</title><description>e-Commerce | Software Development | IT Consulting | IT Management | Information Technology Consulting | Pompeii Consulting</description><link>http://localhost:2368/e-commerce-case-study/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">40bd1757-1dc8-474b-a87a-3af384a1e089</guid><category>e-commerce</category><category>case study</category><category>IT Management</category><category>software development</category><category>Amazon.com</category><category>Harvard Business Review</category><dc:creator>Pompeii Consulting</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 14 Aug 2016 17:02:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;style&gt;  
table, th, td {  
    border: 1px solid black;
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Alibris is an Internet-era company providing search and fulfillment services for hard-to-find (rare, used, and out-of-print) books. At the time of the case, the company had made decisions to change its revenue model, to become involved in the fulfillment process for each book it sells by establishing a cross-dock facility, and to purchase Oracle's Internet commerce software. However, the implementation of this software has been very difficult, delaying the launch of the new fulfillment business and costing large amounts of money at a time when cash is scarce. The company's leaders, who are not IT professionals, must decide whether to continue with Oracle or begin anew with another product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://hbr.org/product/alibris-a/601111-PDF-ENG" target="_blank"&gt;Harvard Business Review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="exercise1"&gt;Exercise 1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="assumptions"&gt;Assumptions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Technology is easy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Integrated information system is possible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="questionstoconsider"&gt;Questions to Consider&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will customers pay for convenience so books can be sold for more than the dealer’s asking price?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will dealers will pay 20% and remain loyal?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will dealers will list all of their books?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can Alibris provide better quality control without impacting delivery time?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can Alibris increase sales?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will new entrants take their customers?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will dealers list with their competitors?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="revenuemodels"&gt;Revenue Models&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;iframe width="100%" height="400" src="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1mWa9ej7v4X4ko9aqGMdm7j5Q4RsO1LBlWu1gN0CrLuk/pubhtml?widget=true&amp;amp;headers=false"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="report"&gt;Report&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id="recommendation"&gt;Recommendation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recommend that Alibris pursue the New Revenue Model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="newrevenuemodel"&gt;New Revenue Model&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h5 id="netincome"&gt;Net Income:&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;table style="width:66%"&gt;  
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th&gt;1999&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th&gt;2000&lt;/th&gt; 
    &lt;th&gt;2001&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;$1,233,000.00&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;$2,169,000.00&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;$3,105,000.00&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id="assumptionshypotheses"&gt;Assumptions/Hypotheses:&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That the $1,872,500 needed to implement this model can be acquired
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;It's 1998. Pets.com&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Revenue model indicates an ROI of less than 1.5 years&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Santa Clara; In Silicon Valley&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customer satisfaction will increase
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Increased accountability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Centralized distribution/order consolidation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;one box&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;one invoice&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="oldrevenuemodel"&gt;Old Revenue Model&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h5 id="netincome"&gt;Net Income:&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;table style="width:66%"&gt;  
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th&gt;1999&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th&gt;2000&lt;/th&gt; 
    &lt;th&gt;2001&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;$139,999.97&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;$235,999.96&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;$331,999.95&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id="assumptionshypotheses"&gt;Assumptions/Hypotheses:&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customer dissatisfaction will eventually drive business away
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Customer experience is not easily monitored&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decentralized, no single point of contact for customers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Current 50-60% fulfillment rate, orders shipped within 2 days&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Competitors will provide better services
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;If it takes $1,872,500 to make the New Revenue Model happen, someone else can make that happen&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="recommendedactions"&gt;Recommended Actions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Obtain funding from outside sources/Venture Capital to fund New Revenue Model &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Asses current employee competency.
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Restructuring base off of findings&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="exercise2"&gt;Exercise 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="assumptions"&gt;Assumptions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The new revenue model is better than the old revenue model&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thunderstone and Oracle are the only options&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="questionstoconsider"&gt;Questions to Consider&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will what worked for eBay work for Alibris?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can Oracle succeed?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will Thunderstone’s software scale?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can Thunderstone solve the locking problem?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is Thunderstone’s software maintainable?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will Thunderstone stay in business?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="report"&gt;Report&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id="recommendation"&gt;Recommendation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recommend that Alibris pursues the Thunderstone Software solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="criteria"&gt;Criteria&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h5 id="finances"&gt;Finances&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Resource utilization, trying to make Oracle work, 3 hires
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Level 1 2,500/month&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consultant Level 2 22,000/month&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Level 2 4,500/month&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoid sunk cost fallacy&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id="deadlines"&gt;Deadlines&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oracle missing deadlines, no identified timeline&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thunderstone waffled whether possible, additional 60-90 days 
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Possible credibility for being honest about feasibility, when first asked &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id="fulfillment"&gt;Fulfillment&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oracle has no known fulfillment date
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Large amount of custom coding required to get to work, not plug and play or up-gradable &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thunderstone "rescued eBay" from a similar situation 
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Thunderstone has a "workaround" to record locking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The infrastructure and hardware for the solution is compatible&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id="language"&gt;Language&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oracle is ubiquitous&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thunderstone require proprietary Vortex
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Hard to find developers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Long term support (LTS) is a concern&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="assumptions"&gt;Assumptions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h5 id="assumption"&gt;Assumption&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thunderstone will be able to solve the locking problem.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id="justification"&gt;Justification&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Claims they have a workaround that they already used for eBay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id="assumption"&gt;Assumption&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alibris won't have to worry, in the near term, about having more traffic than eBay.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id="justification"&gt;Justification&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CEO's own remarks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id="assumption"&gt;Assumption&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thunderstone will be able to speed up queries, search results, and page load times.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id="justification"&gt;Justification&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alibris and eBay have similar business functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="actions"&gt;Actions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check to see if ebay systems are compatible or similar enough to the Alibris hardware.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cut ties with Oracle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recoup funds from Oracle, due to not putting the software into production.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reallocate resources to Thunderstone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evaluate the human capital required for the Thunderstone implementation, namely the three employees hired for the Oracle roll out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clarify whether if Texis is migrating from Vortex to a standard language. Based on result, may need to train in Vortex, start during during 60-90 day implementation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Applied Project</title><description>Emerging Technology | IT Consulting | IT Management | Information Technology Consulting | Information Technology Management | Pompeii Consulting</description><link>http://localhost:2368/applied-project/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">8e58c10b-29dd-4943-9c9a-d1d54950d478</guid><category>information technology</category><category>applied project</category><dc:creator>Pompeii Consulting</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2016 17:31:02 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;This section will be an applied project on emerging information technology issues. All of the concepts, theories, and frameworks learned in earlier sections will be used to develop an information technology backed transformation plan for a business. Effective presentation of this information will also be discussed and demonstrated.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Information Enabled Business Modeling</title><description>Big Data | Data Science | IT Consulting | IT Management | Information Technology Consulting | Information Technology Management | Pompeii Consulting</description><link>http://localhost:2368/information-enabled-business-modeling/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">b449c9cb-f109-40a2-9dba-5a7363c02ed6</guid><category>big data</category><category>analytical culture</category><category>data science</category><category>business strategy</category><category>business intelligence</category><category>data warehouse</category><category>databases</category><category>business modeling</category><dc:creator>Pompeii Consulting</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2016 17:27:50 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;In this section we will look at how different organizations and industries are discovering the value of big data. Further, we will inspect the challenges and short comings of certain approaches and applications. The importance an organizational, analytical culture in conjunction with effective data science to create an informed business strategy is paramount.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>IT Services and Project Management</title><description>IT Services | Project Management | IT Consulting | IT Management | Information Technology Consulting | Pompeii Consulting</description><link>http://localhost:2368/it-services-and-project-management/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">2e8b410f-4434-4772-a959-8b7d12cc4469</guid><category>information technology services</category><category>project management</category><category>commoditization of hardware</category><category>commoditization of software</category><category>business process</category><category>product development process</category><category>service delivery process</category><dc:creator>Pompeii Consulting</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2016 17:18:59 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Information technology services, the commoditization of hardware, the commoditization of software, and the business processes involved will be the main focuses of this section. Time will be spent on the information technology product development processes and on the information technology service delivery processes, with special consideration given to being on-time, on-budget, and meeting end user needs, all while using sound management principles.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Managing Enterprise Systems</title><description>Software Adoption | Emerging Technology | IT Consulting | Information Technology Consulting | Information Technology Management | Pompeii Consulting</description><link>http://localhost:2368/managing-enterprise-systems/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">0aabc773-04ca-4cc3-b3fe-c78024331d7c</guid><category>enterprise systems</category><category>software adoption</category><category>enterprise implementation</category><category>emerging technology</category><category>business enviroment</category><dc:creator>Pompeii Consulting</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2016 17:10:29 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;The major categories of enterprise systems, factors dictating enterprise software adoption, and the fundamentals of enterprise wide implementation will be explored. A major focus will be on the potential impact of emerging technologies on enterprise systems and the business environment as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Emerging Technologies</title><description>Emerging Technology | IT Consulting | IT Management | Information Technology Consulting | Information Technology Management | Pompeii Consulting</description><link>http://localhost:2368/emerging-technologies/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">0081f906-961f-463c-9902-9f3d7a3443e8</guid><category>emerging technology</category><category>integration technology</category><category>mobile platform</category><category>mobile devices</category><category>semantic web</category><category>electronic collaboration</category><dc:creator>Pompeii Consulting</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2016 17:03:58 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;In this section we will look at decision models and decision frameworks to assess, evaluate, and implement emerging technologies. The decision models and decision frameworks will be contextualized with respect to enterprise integration technologies, mobile platforms, mobile devices, semantic web, and electronic collaboration technologies.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Business Process and Workflow Analysis</title><description>Process Analysis | IT Consulting | IT Management | Information Technology Consulting | Information Technology Management | Pompeii Consulting</description><link>http://localhost:2368/business-process-and-workflow-analysis/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">8e161159-ece5-4d9d-941c-0c808a1179bb</guid><category>process analysis</category><category>business process</category><category>workflow analysis</category><dc:creator>Pompeii Consulting</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2016 17:00:38 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;In this section we will look at information, documents, people, roles, and business rules and their importance in process analysis. We will learn how to understand the different business processes involved and how to perform workflow analysis on these processes. Also, attention will be given to rolling out change initiatives within an organization and the possible hurdles and issues that may be encountered.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Information Security and Controls</title><description>COBIT Framework | Data Security | IT Consulting | IT Management | Information Technology Consulting | Information Technology Management | Pompeii Consulting</description><link>http://localhost:2368/information-security-and-controls-2/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">4afe0e58-baca-432c-a91c-49181e325d22</guid><category>COBIT Framework</category><category>information security</category><category>data security</category><category>information controls</category><category>information technology governance</category><dc:creator>Pompeii Consulting</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2016 16:52:24 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Using the COBIT framework we will explore how a wide range of information security, data security, and information controls are designed and implemented. Further, we will look at how this leads to effective information technology governance. &lt;br&gt;
This will help us develop an intuitive understanding of information security and information technology governance. We will then asses the effectiveness of different forms of information security and varying iterations of organizational information security program designs.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Business Intelligence</title><description>Data Warehouse | IT Consulting | IT Management | Information Technology Consulting | Information Technology Management | Pompeii Consulting</description><link>http://localhost:2368/business-intelligence/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">8ffb778a-1094-40a9-aa26-3003cc8d53eb</guid><category>data warehouse</category><category>data warehousing</category><category>data mining</category><category>business intelligence</category><category>BI</category><category>DW</category><category>business analytics</category><category>business performance management</category><category>business</category><category>databases</category><dc:creator>Pompeii Consulting</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2016 16:44:02 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;In this section we will discuss how Business Intelligence (BI) is used by organizations to gain a competitive advantage in the market place. This lays the groundwork for evidence based management decision making, using technologies such as data warehousing, data mining, and contemporary managerial theory: real time business intelligence, business analytics, and business performance management.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>